<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mans last end the glorious vision and fruition of God. By Richard Sheldon Doctor in Divinity, one of his Maiesties chaplines</title>
            <author>Sheldon, Richard, d. 1642?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12093</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102411</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838196</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838196</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2562</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12093)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2562)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1081:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mans last end the glorious vision and fruition of God. By Richard Sheldon Doctor in Divinity, one of his Maiesties chaplines</title>
                  <author>Sheldon, Richard, d. 1642?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 109, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones dwelling in Red-crosse-streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2562:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2562:1"/>
            <p>MANS LAST END, THE GLORIOVS VISI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON AND FRV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ITION OF GOD. By <hi>Richard Sheldon</hi> Doctor in Divinity, one of his Maieſties Chaplines.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Ioh. 3. 2.</bibl>
               <p>Wee know that when he ſhall appeare wee ſhall be like him, for wee ſhall ſee him as he is.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by WILLIAM IONES dwelling in Red-croſſe-ſtreete, 1634.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2562:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2562:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTIE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>DREAD</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Overaigne, Sacred and divine is Royall <hi>MAIESTIE,</hi> and it is the glorie thereof to protect ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred things. This my Meditation vpon Heavens Loadſtone, the glorious viſion &amp; fruition of God, though in reſpect of the authour and the ſtile, it may ſeeme unworthy of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties iudicious eye; yet in regard it is in it ſelfe aſubiect moſt ſacred, and ſacredly handled (agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the rule of holy faith) I humbly preſume to crave from your Maieſty both pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ection, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious acceptance of it; which my minde preſumes, I ſhall moſt aſſuredly haue: Protection, becauſe I humbly craue it, from the Defender of that faith, the happy end and fruite whereof, is the glorious viſion and fruition of God: Gracious acceptance, becauſe it cannot but be a ſubiect moſt acceptable to your religious and pious mind, which (like that of <hi>Moſes</hi>) is daily looking on this moſt glorious
<pb facs="tcp:2562:3"/> reward. For this (to the ioy of your people, and for the example of all greatneſſe) Comes teſtified &amp; confirmed, both by your Maieſties reverent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to the word Read or Preached; fervent and intentiue devotion to Gods prayſes (in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers) celebrated; but eſpecially by your Maieſties daily often times of prayers. O that the whole <hi>Britaine</hi>-Orbe, at leaſt the whole Tribe of <hi>Levy</hi> therein, were compoſed and ordered, according to this your Maieſties example. Goe on glorious Prince, &amp; let not your Hand ceaſe to protect &amp; enlarge the virgine-faith which yee profeſſe, to raiſe up deſpiſed Diſcipline, (for the glory of our Church), to mainteyne iuſtice and iudgement, and with Clemency to eſtabliſh your Throne. And that glorious God whom yee ſerue with feare &amp; trembling, ſhall, and will in the end, bid you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into that his owne ioye, the glorious viſion and fruition of himſelfe.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Excellent Majeſties loyall ſubiect and ſervant, Richard Sheldon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2562:3"/>
            <head>To the Religious Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader whoſoever thou art, into whoſe hands this Treatiſe may come; I adviſe thee that howſoever this diamond of thy felicity come thus rudely (yet clearly and truely) preſented unto thee, thou make ſuch good uſe of this and the like, that thou mayeſt happily in the end enjoy the glory it ſelfe. Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hereon thou wilt eaſily ſee how degenerate thou art from thy owne Originall dignity, if by the contagion of unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented ſinne, thou deprive thy ſelfe of that gemme which God hath prepared for thee, and all thoſe that feare him, and love his comming. Had the naturall Sages of the world knowne this end of man, whereas ſome of them, as the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians called him a little world, an Earthly God: Others, as the Egiptians and their Triſmegistus, the miracle of the world, they would in reſpect of the glory expected and to be revealed, have termed him the miracle of heaven, a glorious companion by grace, of majeſty it ſelfe, thus entring into, and diving into, the Lords owne Ioy it ſelfe. But whence hath man this, but from the free grace of the Father? By whom hath hee this, but by the humble obedience of the Sonne to the Father? By what, all this? but by obedient faith in the Saviour; The firſt is the fountaine; the ſecond, is the way and meane of this glory: the third is the condition without which, this glory is not obtained. O then having found this moſt precious diamond, and from whom it is; God the Father: By whom it is; Christ Ieſus the Sonne: for whom it is: the faithfull and loving beleevers. Preſſe thou on to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the marke, for the price of this high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus, the glorious viſion and fruition of God himſelfe.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in CHRIST IESVS, RICHARD SHELDON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2562:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE BOOKE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Section 1. Sheweth joyntly wherein the nature and condition of an end and laſt end may conſiſt.</item>
               <item>Sect. 2. Wherein is joyntly ſhewed by ſundry argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and cleare demonſtrations, that the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of humane felicity or laſt end of man, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be riches, pleaſures, nor honour; taken ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, or joyntly. pag. 9.</item>
               <item>Sect. 3. Shewing that God onely is the laſt end of man, and his finall happineſſe. pag. 18.</item>
               <item>Sect. 4. God being the object of mans happineſſe, and his laſt end, it is ſhewed by what union, he is knitte, and united to the Soule, and thereby the Soule made happy. pag. 25.</item>
               <item>Sect. 5. Wherein is more particularly handled, in what action, or actions, the laſt happineſſe of man, doth ſpecially conſiſt. pag. 50.</item>
               <item>Sect. 6, Conteines certaine obſervations, touching the glorified bodies of the beatified and their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious qualities. pag. 63.</item>
               <item>Sect. 7. Wherein is breefely and in generall laid downe the meanes and way, whereby eternall happines is to be attained. pag. 92.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2562:4"/>
            <head>MANS LAST END, THE GLORIOVS VISION AND FRVITION OF GOD.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>Firſt Section, ſhewing Ioyntly wherein the nature and condition of an end and laſt end may conſiſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE nature and eſſence of an end in generall, is to be <hi>that for which another thing is intended, as a meanes to attaine the ſame end.</hi> Or<note place="margin">Wherein the nature of an end doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> thus, An end, is that which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to motion or action: which reſpect and formality of an end, in the laſt end requires further, that it be that for which all other things are intended, and it not for any one of them ſingly taken, no, nor for all of them taken together and unitedly: Whence from by ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitable conſequence it followeth, that the laſt end of man is, that to which all the actions of man, yea man himſelfe is to be referred; as being that, by which and in which, his full reſt and laſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is intended. Herehence it alſo followeth moſt clearely; firſt, that the laſt end of man, muſt needs be farre better than man, and all that is in man; as being that which muſt give full
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2562:5"/> perfection and reſt to man, and all that is in man. The end finall is ever better than that which is for the end; the houſe is better than the lime, timber and ſtone, which are for the houſe; and man better than the houſe, for whoſe uſe the houſe is, ſo the end of man better then man,</p>
               <p>Secondly, the laſt end of man muſt be ſuch as doth fully ſatiate and quiet all the deſires of man; for that is the laſt end of every thing, which when it is had, giveth perfect reſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. <hi>Auſtin, Truly wee ſay that to be the laſt end of man, not wherewith he is ſo conſumed as that he ceaſeth to be, but that wherewith he is ſo perfited that he may fully and perfectly be;</hi> By which it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that the inordinate love of mans owne ſelfe, is fartheſt off, from being the laſt end of a mans owne ſelfe; for an inordinate mind is ever a puniſhment and affliction to it ſelfe. In <hi>Austins</hi> phraſe; <hi>God hath made us for himſelfe, and unquiet is mans heart untill it attaine him.</hi> This nature of an end thus breifly laid open, two things will clearely apeare, The firſt, that man in all his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<note place="margin">Man hath an end in all his actions.</note> hath ſome ſpeciall end, againe, that of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and all his actions he hath a laſt and totall end.</p>
               <p>Concerning the firſt, that man hath an end in all his actions, what man that hath the leaſt ſpaeke of humane knowledge in him is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded? yea more; who hath arightly thought of man and all other earthly creatures, can other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thinke, but that man, onely man, doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto himſelfe ſome ſpeciall end in all his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2562:5"/> actions; yea a laſt end, for which and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of which, he doth and intends all he either doth or intendeth. <hi>Senſleſſe</hi> creatures, worke not otherwiſe too and for their ends, but for that without all ſenſe or knowledge, they by a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall poyſe bend and are inclined to their ends. <hi>Senſitiue</hi> creatures worke too and for their ends, though not knowne to them under the formality of an end, yet apprehended by them as the thing unto which for their reſt and perfection their nature doth encline them, ſo that they are rather driven and enforced by a naturall propenſion then moved by apprehenſion and cogitation. This truth if dayly experience did not make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, yet cleare reaſon doth evince it; for there is not any creature whether ſenſitive or ſenſleſſe which hath not ſome inclination and proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereby it is wayed to ſome ſpeciall good; which good being that for the attaining whereof it is inclined, we muſt and doe call the ſame an end, either partiall or totall.</p>
               <p>And although all ſenſitiue and ſenſleſſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures have one and the ſame laſt remote end, not knowne to themſelves, but intended by God, <hi>who hath made all things for himſelfe,</hi> yet their<note place="margin">Fro. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſpeciall and peculiarends, are ſeverall and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed; being no other than a naturall conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation or enlarging of themſelues: A very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect paterne of that inordinate love, (the very ſtones and mortar wherewith the tower of <hi>Babell</hi> to the contempt of <hi>God</hi> is built) which every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate man hath of himſelfe: for as the ſenſitive
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2562:6"/> creature hath no other end than by ſatisfying his luſt to conſerve it ſelfe, ſo the inordinate man hath no other end, but the <hi>ſelfe content</hi> and fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of himſelfe; he referrs all things, yea <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his religion (aſmuch as may lye in his power) to himſelfe and for his owne content; which is the greateſt iniquity, <hi>to uſe the things which ought to be injoyed, and to injoy thoſe things, which ought onely to be uſed.</hi> And although theſe brutiſh ſenſitiue and <hi>Animall</hi> men have no other end of themſelves but themſelves, <hi>Lovers of themſelues more than of God,</hi> yet <hi>God</hi> ordeines<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 2. Pro. 16. 4. Ier. 46. 11.</note> them to another end, <hi>the evill day, the day of anger and of ſlaughter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It being thus apparent, that ſenſitive vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſenſleſſe and inanimate creatures, have their ſeverall inclinations, either innate or upon apprehenſion, by which they are urgently and neceſſarily carried to their ſeverall ends; more apparent it muſt be, that man in ſuch his actions as are humane, is ſwayed in and unto them all, upon the apprehenſion of ſome good by him intended and proſecuted, wherein the formality and nature of an end doth properly conſiſt.</p>
               <p>And we muſt not onely thinke, that man in his ſeverall particular actions, hath ſome particular good things after which he aimerh as the ends of the ſame, but we are further to underſtand, that every man hath ſome totall compleat laſt end, both of himſelfe, and all his actions, in things which are ordeined one for another, as are the actions of man, every man; there cannot be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2562:6"/> into an infinity; <hi>In cauſes finall, or ends, there cannot be progreſſe infinite,</hi> ſay the Schooles, and the reaſon is manifeſt; for an end, is not an end but as it moveth: now if there were an infinitie in the ends, there could be no mooving nor motion at all; for that is infinite which never can be paſſed over, nor mooved unto, either in finite time or by a finite cauſe: And againe, ſecond cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes mooue not unleſſe they be mooved; but over an infinite diſtance there is no mooving; ſo then if there were an infinite progreſſe in cauſes finall, there could be no mooving at all, and therefore of neceſſity it muſt be graunted, that man hath<note place="margin">How every man intendeth ſome end.</note> ſome laſt totall compleate end, to which he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deineth himſelfe and all his actions. Only it is to be obſerved, that every man doth ſo ordeine himſelfe and his actions to ſome laſt full end, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vainely, interpretatively, and by vaine ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, or elſe, truely, and deliberately by ſett reſolution. I ſaid vainely and interpretative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>vainely,</hi> thereby to deſigne the impious and ungodly, who upon vaine imaginations, doe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſett unto themſelves ſome vaine fading object, as their end and laſt happineſſe; I ſaid <hi>interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively,</hi> for how ſoever the wicked and ungodly,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> whoſe thoughts and affections are ſcattered, <hi>as duſt before the wind, do in words</hi> pretend <hi>God,</hi> to be their laſt end, yet ſeeing they vainely ſolace them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the fruition of the creature, contrary to the will of God; and thereby commit wilfull ſinne (which is a <hi>ſeparation wall betwixt God and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 59<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>themſelves</hi>) they are interpreted to make the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2562:7"/> and not the creator their laſt end; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly their <hi>God</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>their belly,</hi> their<note place="margin">Phi. 3. 19. Col. 3. 4. Luc. 12. 19.</note> gold their <hi>idoll,</hi> their ſtore houſes and barns the <hi>centers</hi> of their reſt and repoſe; by which meanes (what ſoever elſe they may preſume or pretend) they are for all eternity, to be ſeparated from <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe I ſaid (vainely) for how vaine is it for<note place="margin">By vaine ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination.</note> any man to make that his laſt end, which ought not to be any end at all, or that to be laſt end of man (to weet, delightfull ſinne) the end whereof is hell and deſtruction; <hi>for the wages of ſinne is</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>death, death eternall.</hi> O, how vainely then walke ſinners in the vanity of their ſenſe; having their<note place="margin">Epleſ. 4. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>vnderſtandings obſcured through the blindneſſe of their hearts, which is in them.</hi> Excellently ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that the underſtanding is obſcured, through the blindneſſe of the heart; for ſo blind are they that though they love ſinne immoderat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet they preſume that they ſerue God obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiouſly, O the lamentable (yet unlamented) blindneſſe of willfull ſinners! O the fearefull ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of <hi>God,</hi> thus chaſtening preſumption! <hi>Austen</hi> fitly to this purpoſe, <hi>If any robbing, ſhould</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Pſa. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>thereby in the very act loſe his ſight, every man would ſay that Gods judgement was preſent: but having lost the eyes of our minds, we thinke God to be both ſparing</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Indg. 16. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>and indulgent. Sampſon</hi> could not be brought to grind in the mill before his eyes were plucked out; ſo, ſo, neither could the <hi>Devill</hi> draw men to ſo ſervile a bondage of ſinne, to place happineſſe in that which inevitably leadeth to death and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2562:7"/> unleſſe he had firſt deprived him of the light of his mind. I ſaid above that the laſt end in ſome is truely, directly and deliberatly inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; to ſhew the very manner, how the true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of <hi>God</hi> doe preſet and prefixe vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>God</hi> and his glory for the laſt totall and compleat end of themſelves, and all their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that <hi>whether they eate or drinke, or what elſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>they do in word or worke, they do all to the glory of God,</hi> alwayes and in al things giuing tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks to God<note place="margin">Col. 3. 17.</note> and the Father by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> But I muſt not on to faſt, and involue this truth with obſcurity; I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate againe theſe words <hi>Truly, directly</hi> and <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beratly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sap. 7. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Truly for that into feined ſoules and deceitfull minds, wiſdome will not enter,</hi> but onely unto ſuch as thinke of <hi>God in goodneſſe, and in the ſincerity of their heart do ſeeke him. Directly,</hi> to ſhew that the Archer aimeth not more directly at the white in the ſhooting, than the ſervant of God doth looke on God in working. To him his ſoule walketh, on him his ſoule wayteth, after him his ſoule thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth,<note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> yea to him both ſoule and fleſh is manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faſtned and fixed. I ſay deliberately, to ſhew, that the ſoule not onely upon a firſt motion and as it were by an impetuoſity of ſanctified nature, is bent and inclined to God, but that vpon cleare conſideration he doth moſt fervently purſue and intend after God, only God.</p>
               <p>That of the Schooles is moſt true: <hi>The cauſality of the end is the reaſon of all,</hi> becauſe the firſt that mooveth and the moover of all other cauſes; So in God, ſo in all intelligent creatures, the end
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2562:8"/> prefixed mooves all: which end in God (though without himſelfe he ordeined one thing for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; Grace for Glory, damnation for ſinne, (only ſinne) is no other than <hi>himſelfe,</hi> his owne glory; mooving himſelfe to doe all things for the ſame. In like ſort, the end is that, which firſt mooveth in all intelligent creatures; how then can it be, but that the end is <hi>truly, directly &amp; deliberatly</hi> intended? whenas for the attaining of it all other things are intended, it being the good one that guids and directs all.</p>
               <p>Againe, ſay the Schooles and truly, <hi>The end is purſued without meaſure,</hi> but thoſe things which are for the end, according as the further and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce unto the end; how then ſhall not the laſt end be purſued directly and deliberatly, yea with a<note place="margin">Mat. 22. 33.</note> ſweet kind of impetuoſſity and violence of <hi>Grace,</hi> with the <hi>whole heart, all the ſoule, with the whole mind, and with all the ſtrength of him,</hi> who arightly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends the end. This <hi>David</hi> feelingly profeſſes<note place="margin">Pſal. 42. 1.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he thus breathes out. <hi>Even as the Hart pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth after the fountaines of waters, ſo my ſoule thirſteth and longeth after thee O my God.</hi> Herehence it is, that in ſo much every thing is the more perfect, in how much it is more efficaciouſly ordered and directed to the end: and that as in naturall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the neerer the end the ſwifter the motions are, ſo in motions of grace and ſupernall, the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to <hi>God,</hi> the ſwifter and the more ſweetly vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and efficacious the motions are. So, ſo the ſoule which living only deſireth <hi>God,</hi> delighted<note place="margin">Pſal. 73. 25.</note> on <hi>God,</hi> dying and parting from the body, longeth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2562:8"/> and panteth only after God, nothing but God.</p>
               <p>Yet againe ſaith the Schooles, and truly: <hi>That all things</hi> which (as meanes) <hi>are for, and conduce to the end, are not intended nor proſecuted but</hi> out of a <hi>deliberate and full intention of the end.</hi> So then in man there can be no deliberate actions but ſuch as are intended either for the true and happy end of all, God; or elſe for ſuch imagined and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ends which the corruption of man preſets vnto himſelfe. <hi>Auſten</hi> excellently; <hi>That is the end of all our good, for which all other things are loved, and it for it ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have wee ſhewed (though breefely, yet ſufficiently) that man, every man hath not only in all his ſeverall and particular actions ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall privat ends, but further alſo, that man, every man hath ſome compleate and finall end both of himſelfe and of all his actions: But what is the laſt end of man?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>THE SECOND SECTION.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein is ioyntly ſhewed by ſundry arguments and cleare demonſtrations, that the obiect of humane felicity or laſt end of man, cannot be riches, pleaſures nor honours; taken ſeverally, or ioyntly.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THough common experience excludes from being the object of humane felicity or laſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2562:9"/> end of man, that three headed monſter, <hi>concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>of the fleſh, luſt of the eyes, and pride of life,</hi> (joyntly or ſeverally taken) wherein the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> confines, all that is excellent, delightfull, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable in the world; yet by way of prelude to our following diſcourſe, I have thought good to adde a few morall reaſons and demonſtrations eight in a perfect number, that theſe three which are (formally or reductively) all that is excellent, pleaſant or proffitable in the world, whether ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnitedly together, or apart, are not the laſt end of man or the obiect of his felicity, for which<note place="margin">1 Reaſon.</note> purpoſe I argue thus firſt: The object of mans felicity, or laſt end of man, muſt, in reſpect of that which is cheefe in man (to weet, the ſoule of man) be ſo perfect that it muſt give full content<note place="margin">The laſt end of man muſt give full content to man.</note> and reſt thereunto; that is, to man as man; But out alaſſe! who ever, (whoſe ſoule hath beene en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with leaſt ſparke of wiſdome) hath found full content in riches, honour or pleaſures; againſt which <hi>Salomon</hi> the wiſeſt amongſt all the wiſe, exclaimes; <hi>O the vanity of vanities and all vanity.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecl. 1.</note> Yea ſo contrary is the operation of theſe to the wiſdome of the ſoule, that to ſurfet with theſe, is to pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in reaſon, to languiſh in piety, and<note place="margin">Eph. 4. 18.</note> with deepeſt ignorance to have the ſoule obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and darkned. And ſurely by theſe <note n="*" place="margin">Occaſionaly</note> the <hi>God of this world</hi> doth blind the hearts of ſuch as doe periſh. And in this reſpect, is Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>han called <hi>God</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>of this world;</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cauſe by theſe three (as it were the life and marrow of the world) (pride, riches, pleaſures, glory, &amp;c.) He hath abuſively rule
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2562:9"/> and reigneth over the children of <hi>miſbeleefe</hi> and <hi>diſohedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly: the laſt end or felicity of man, muſt<note place="margin">Second reaſon</note> be ſo good, that no man may uſe the ſame ill; but theſe both joyntly and ſeverally taken; are ſuch as by the poſſeſſiones of them, may be uſed ſo ill, that for the abuſing of them, they may with the <hi>reprobate glutton</hi> periſh eternally; yea they are ſo<note place="margin">Luk. 16. 15.</note> fit and apt to be ill uſed, that they carry with them a croſſe barre of difficulty, if (not of impoſſibility,) of being well uſed, or that ſalvation may be obteined by the poſeſſioners of them; for ſo we are to underſtand that of the Sonne of <hi>God; It</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 19. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>is eaſier for a Camell, to paſſe through the eye of a nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle,</hi> than for a rich man, to enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Heaven.</hi> Some of the wiſer <hi>Ancients,</hi> to expreſſe the difficulty, which pleaſures, honour, and riches, do bring againſt the exerciſe of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, have feigned a Virgin (by name <hi>Aclanta</hi>) of ſuch admirable beauty, that the Worthies of that time, were all enamoured with the love of her: but as her beauty was ſurpaſſing great, ſo was her ſwiftneſſe in running farre greater, ſo that in running ſhee could not be overtaken, by any of the Valiants of thoſe times; though ſhe had often proffered her ſelfe to be his, who in running could out go her: At laſt, one <hi>Hippomenes,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents himſelfe unto her, who that the better he might obteine his purpoſe, in out running the faire <hi>Aclanta,</hi> had ſecretly provided three balls of gold, the which, one after one, as they were in their courſe of running, he caſts before her; for the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2562:10"/> taking up of which the beautifull maid makes ſuch ſtayes and ſo many ſtops, that ſhee was out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runne by <hi>Hippomenes,</hi> and ſo was obteined of him. Now who is this faire <hi>Atlanta,</hi> but the ſoule of man, adorned with ſundry heavenly graces? whoſe power (by grace,) was to have not ſinned, but to have ſtood and continued in grace; had ſhee not beene overtaken and over priſed, in the courſe of her obedience, by the infernall <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pomenes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Firſt apple of Pleaſures; the forbidden fruit: the 2 of pride you ſhal be like God: the 3 of Covetouſneſſe, knowing good and evill. Gen: 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. 5.</note> who, caſting before her, the three b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lls of riches, pleaſures, and honoures, letted her from the attaining of that glory, and happineſſe for which ſhee was made and deſigned. Thus are riches eagerly deſired, <hi>and heaped</hi> up for the hurt of the poſſeſſioner; So are honours, the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes of <hi>Satan,</hi> blowing up the fire of arrogancy; So are pleaſures, the ſnares and gives of <hi>Satan,</hi> wherewith he leades ſenſuall minds, captives to that place of torments, where ſuch a meaſure of torments ſhall be given according as the guilty ſhall be found, to have exceeded in the riot of their pleaſures.</p>
               <p>The third reaſon I frame thus. The happineſſe<note place="margin">Third reaſon.</note> of man, muſt be ſuch that as no man can uſe it ill, ſo muſt it not have any evill unavoydable accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying and adjoyned with it. But what ſweet, proffitable or glorious thing is there in the world, which hath not ever, ſome evill either, of bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or diſproffit, or diſhonour, or infirmity of the body, or anxiety of the minde, intermixt therewith? that whoſoever ſhall ſett his ſoule, upon any thing, or all the things that are in this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2562:10"/> world, he cannot but be thought to have received his ſoule in vaine, &amp; reſting upon vanity, what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe for ſuch a <hi>ſoule, to have gained the world, if</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 16. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>it periſh with the world?</hi> and what a felicity to have gained the world, when as all that is in the world is but a puffe of vanity? <hi>Seneca</hi> very excellently, <hi>O how ridiculous is the boundes of mortall men? it is but a point, which with ſword and fier, is devided into ſo many nations; above there are infinite ſpaces, into the poſſeſſion whereof the ſoule may be admitted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, I argue thus; The laſt end of man,<note place="margin">Fourth reaſon.</note> (becauſe the laſt, and becauſe of man, who in his ſoule is <hi>immortall,</hi> and never dieth) muſt be alſo immortall, never dye nor fade away; but who ſeeth not, by dayly experience, that of the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Apostle</hi> to be moſt true: <hi>The world and the lust</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>thereof paſſeth away?</hi> If then that be true (as it is moſt true) <hi>that, that cannot be true happines, the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity whereof is not certeine;</hi> then aſſuredly, that cannot be the matter and object of true happineſſe, whoſe inſtability, and dayly mutability is moſt certeine. <hi>Salomon</hi> having had a full taſte (even to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiety) of all the glorious delicacyes of the world, cries out with a moſt humble note and loud crie, <hi>O the vanity of vanityes; and all things vanity; O the vanity of vanityes!</hi> Vanity then, and moſt vaine, ſhould the laſt end of man then be, if placed in ſuch <hi>vanities</hi> of honours, riches, or pleaſures.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, the laſt end naturall of man, is that<note place="margin">Fifth reaſon.</note> whereunto by God (as Author of nature) he is ordeined; the laſt end ſupernaturall, is that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto God (as the Author of <hi>Grace</hi>) hath deſigned
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2562:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2562:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2562:12"/> and ordeined him: But cleare it is, and it needs no proofe, that all the good terrene things of the world, cannot be the end ſupernaturall, for which man was made; and as eaſily it is ſhewed, that they cannot be the end naturall of man; for as it hath beene already prooved, they let and hinder man, from the atcheiving of his ſupernaturall ends: <hi>But as Grace, hurts not, but perfects nature;</hi> ſo nature, as nature (though as vitiated it hinders) hinders not Grace, but being elevated and <hi>renewed by</hi> Grace, is by Grace made able to be concurrent with <hi>Grace.</hi> O with how few things is nature ordinate content! <hi>Socrates</hi> the wiſe and temperate, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſuperfluity of humane cares, cries out, <hi>O how many things are there which I do not want!</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, do we not ſee, that honours, riches, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially pleaſures, are very frequently attendant up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe, in whom nature is rather deſtroyed and corrupted, than in part impaired or diminiſhed? Of ſuch manner of men the Apoſtle <hi>Iude</hi> very fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly: <hi>That in thoſe things which they naturally know,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iud. epiſt v. 10</note> (not as man but as brute beaſts) <hi>in them they are corrupted.</hi> It is true, that as God often favours the famous in giving them wealth, ſo ſinn for moſt part infatuates where God giveth wealth, ſo that the wealthy as they often glory inordinately in honour; ſo they ſurfet immoderately in Pleaſures. And where are the perſons that do not ſo? Let the Iovinianiſts of latter times be an example for all. And who obſerves not; that this tendes not to the perfection but to the corruption of nature?</p>
               <p>Sixtly, the laſt end of man muſt bee immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Sixth reaſon.</note>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2562:12"/> attained, poſſeſſed, injoyed by the beſt and cheefeſt actions, which are in man, to weet, the actions of the cheefeſt powers, and faculties of the ſoule; the will, and underſtanding. But riches, pleaſures, honour, fame glory, are immediately apprehended, felt, and injoyed, by the outward ſenſes of man; and do only appertaine to the ſoule, by the way of approvance or rejectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; for the good and uſefull ſervice of her body, and ſenſuall parts; for the ſoule, being ſpirituall and immateriall, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have, or receive any immediate impreſſions, from things corporall, and materiall. Which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, and moſt clearely ſo; how idle were it, in theſe corporall and materiall things, to place the laſt end of man, and to make them, the object of his happineſſe and felicity?</p>
               <p>Seventhly, as the cheefeſt actions of the ſoule,<note place="margin">Seventh reaſon</note> muſt be the immediate apprehenſion, poſſeſſion, and fruition, of thoſe things, which muſt be the<note place="margin">The laſt end of man muſt bee the cheefeſt good that man can attaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</note> laſt end of man; ſo the cheefeſt good and beſt thing which the ſoule, can <hi>attaine</hi> unto by <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> can embrace by <hi>love;</hi> can injoy by <hi>delight;</hi> muſt be his laſt end and the object of his happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; felicity. Now to thinke of any other thing for this purpoſe beſides <hi>God,</hi> were the greateſt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that might be imagined: For, not ſpeaking onely of things ſublunary, but even the celeſtiall<note place="margin">Gen. 1. 17.</note> themſelves; what are they all, but either images (as men and Angells) or <hi>footings,</hi> or ſhadowes of<note place="margin">Pſa. 19.</note> the creator himſelfe, as all other creatures are? And what a vanity were it, to thinke, that the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi> of the Creator, ſhould have for the object
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2562:13"/> of her happineſſe and laſt end, thoſe things, which are onely as footings or darke foote impreſſions of the Creator? Or how vaine to thinke, that thoſe things which are made for the uſe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of man (as all terrene things were) ſhould be the end of man? Sweetly was this underſtood by moſt Intelligent <hi>David,</hi> who ballancing all things that were in the heavens above, or on the earth belowe; cries out, <hi>What is there for me in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 73.</note> 
                  <hi>And beſides thee what would I upon earth, the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 9. Pſa. 23. 25. 26</note> 
                  <hi>God of my heart, and portion for ever?</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, <hi>O thou my God,</hi> thou, thou that<note place="margin">A moſt divine elevation of Davids ſpirit.</note> art my ever and laſt end; the very joy and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of my hart; how glorious thou in the heavens above? and what happineſſe is there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for me in thee? above? how then may I, or can I, take full content or delight in any thing that is here below? <hi>Baſill</hi> elegantly, compares them, that fixe their <hi>hearts</hi> upon any earthly good thing whatſoever, (appretiating them before God) to him, who hearing ſome exquiſite and moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Doctor,</hi> preaching, or teaching out of a chaire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſtanding in the Sunne, ſhould (neglecting both the Teacher, his words, and geſtures) attend and obſerve only the ſhadow of the teacher, and ſuch ſeverall motions, or geſtures, as are repreſented thereby; So he very excellently, accounting all the beſt, and good creatures of God (being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to God,) to be no more, nor better (indeed they are not ſomuch) than the ſhadow of the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and his geſtures, (repreſented therein) are, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compared to the Teacher himſelfe, and unto
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2562:13"/> his actions of life.</p>
               <p>Eightly, and laſtly, as the underſtanding of<note place="margin">Eight reaſon.</note> man, is by nature apt, and hath an apprehenſive power to apprehend all that is <hi>cognoſcible,</hi> or may<note place="margin">God onely can be the full ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of mans knowledge and love.</note> be knowne or vnderſtood, vnder the condition of truth; ſo the will of man, (whoſe proper object is good) as by nature it embraceth nothing but what is good, or under the apparance of good; ſo it hath a propenſion and inclination, to purſue all good, either to be attained diſperſedly in ſeverall creatures; or in ſome one <hi>fountaine</hi> and roote of all <hi>goodneſſe:</hi> which inclinations, both of the will and underſtanding, unleſſe they be fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied and quieted, by that cheefeſt good, and pureſt truth (which is, and are the laſt end, and object of their happineſſe) they ſhall never be found, truly to have attained their laſt end and finall happineſſe. But if we conſider, the moſt glorious, of <hi>Gods</hi> creatures; in no one; no, in no one million of them, can be found, all that may be underſtood by the underſtanding; or be deſired and embraced by the will; and conſequently, no one of them; nor no infinite multitude of them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, can be the full object of mans laſt end, and happineſſe: no; <hi>God, God</hi> alone is this pureſt truth, and cheefeſt good, the full and compleate object, both of the wills and underſtandings, of all his Intelligent creatures; who being preſented to the beautified Soules, enabled with the light of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to <hi>ſee him as he is in himſelfe, even face to face;</hi> how unenarrable, unſpeakeable and incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible, is the <hi>joy</hi> of ſuch Soules, ſo intuitively
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2562:14"/> beholding? ſo joyouſly poſſeſſing of their <hi>God,</hi> and moſt ſweetly delighting in their God? Of this Ambroſe ſweetly; <hi>What good better</hi> then this <hi>good, What felicity greater then this, to live to God,</hi> in <hi>God, and to live of God? Bernard</hi> like himſelfe divinely:<note place="margin">Barnard ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m, 31 in Canti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a.</note> 
                  <hi>To whom God appeareth, they will ſee nothing more deſiredly; nor can ſee nothing more delightfully: when then, will either deſire of ſeeing lothe, or</hi> ſweetneſſe <hi>withdraw herſelfe, or truth deceive, or aeternity fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le, to whom, opportunity of ſeeing, and a will to ſee is graunted</hi> for <hi>ever and ever? how then ſhall their felicity not be full? for nothing is either wanting to them, that alwayes ſee, or is tedious to them, who have a deſire al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to ſee: but this viſion is not of this preſent life, but is reſerved for the laſt end of man.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>THIRD SECTION.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Shewing that God onely is the laſt end of man, and his finall happineſſe.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>VVHen I thinke of that precept of <hi>God,</hi> knowne by the lawe of nature, directed by the law of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> renewed in the law of grace; <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy</hi> God <hi>with all thy heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 6. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>with all thy ſoule, with all thy</hi> ſtrength, and with all <hi>thy mind,</hi> I cannot but make a ſpeedy reſolution,<note place="margin">Mat. 22. 37.</note> who, and what is the laſt end of mans heart, his ſoule, his ſtrength, and his mind; for if <hi>God</hi> be to be beloved with the whole heart, ſoule, minde, and ſtrength of man, it were a vanity and a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ke any other laſt end for man then God.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2562:14"/> Nay love, as ſaith <hi>Auſten</hi> (very excellently) <hi>Is my weight and poyſe, with it, and by it I am carried whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſoever</hi> I am <hi>carried.</hi> A totall and compleat love then of the whole heart, Soule, and minde, of man, and all that is in man, cannot other whither carry him, or leade him, then to that which is the very center of his reſt, and happineſſe. <hi>Thou fast made us O Lord for thee, and unquiet is our heart till it come to thee:</hi> and <hi>Boetius</hi> very fitly: <hi>We muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity confeſſe, that God is the very bleſſedneſſe of man.</hi> But when we affirme, that God is the laſt end of man and his finall happineſſe, we muſt for the clearer underſtanding of the ſame, diſtinguiſh thus: the laſt end of man and his happineſſe, may be<note place="margin">A neceſſary di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction.</note> conſidered in two ſorts; either the laſt end (which) or the laſt end (wherewith;) or thus in other termes; the objective beatitude of man, or the <hi>formall</hi> beatitude of man. I explaine my ſelfe: The end, (<hi>which</hi>) is that, which is the very thing, where in the ſoule of man, doth finally reſt, and eternally joy it ſelfe: the end (wherewith) are the cheifeſt action or actions; operation or operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſoule, wherewith the end attained is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, and poſſeſſed: In like ſort, the objective beatitude, is the very object, whereon theſe cheife actions are exerciſed, which the Soule ſeeing and enjoying, is thereby made happy; <hi>Beatitude</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall, is the very ſeeing, enjoying and poſſeſſing of this object. We may take ſome familiar exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hereof; To the avaritious Perſon (who ſhould indeed have only God for his lott and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) <hi>his end, which is</hi> his Mony, and whatſoever
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2562:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2562:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:2562:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2562:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2562:17"/> elſe, is for Money eſtimable; his end (wherewith) is his baſe whoording up, increaſing, and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſame: The Intemperate mans end (which is every voluptuous thing,) he takes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in his end (wherewith) is his ſolace, pleaſure, and delight which he takes therein even ſo the laſt end of man (wherewith) is the adeption and frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God; the end (which) is God himſelfe, ſo injoyed and poſſeſſed.</p>
               <p>It is true, that God who is his owne end eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially,<note place="margin">God happy by himſelfe.</note> both objective and formall; is not happy by any any thing that is without himſelfe, or that is dependently of himſelfe, but as he is eſſentially his owne exiſtence and being, ſo is hee eſſentially his owne happy being: <hi>Auſten</hi> excellently; <hi>what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is in God,</hi> is <hi>God, there</hi> is no accidentall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paction or compoſition; So then <hi>God</hi> being hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in himſelfe, and by himſelfe; himſelfe is both the object of his happineſſe, and his owne formall happineſſe. But creatures intelligent, to weet, men and <hi>Angells,</hi> having not an infinite and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall happineſſe, but a happineſſe only by parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation, can have the ſame by no other meanes, nor wayes, then by ſome limited operations, and actions of their intellectuall parts, underſtanding and will; which actions and operations muſt needs have ſome happy and ſingular object, wherein and whereon they are converſant and exerciſed; which object alſo muſt or can, fully ſatiate, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and glad the ſoule; which that it is <hi>God,</hi> the one onely, cheefe, and infinite good of the ſoule, is ſo cleare and evident, that it were dotage to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2562:17"/> ſtand long in the proofe of the ſame. And though it be moſt cleare, that <hi>God,</hi> onely <hi>God,</hi> is this laſt object, which onely muſt and can give happineſſe<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 11.</note> unto the Soule, yet ſo obſcured are the hearts of ſome fooliſh men, that though they cannot ſay in their hearts there is no <hi>God,</hi> yet they ſay that <hi>God</hi> is not the laſt end of their ſoules, nor the object of their happineſſe. But O that they would conſider, and ſeriouſly ponder in their ſoules, oh, how eaſily ſhould they finde in <hi>God</hi> all reaſons, that might moove them to take him, and to embrace him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for their laſt end; and the totall object of their happineſſe? Where there is an infinite pyle of wood kindled, it cannot bee but the fier kindled may burne for an infinite time, and without end; how then ſhall not the ſoule infinitely, and for ever<note place="margin">In God is all that is to bee beloved.</note> burne with love; and joy it ſelfe with delight; which hath God (in whom there is an infinite abyſſe of goodneſſe, power, Majeſty, beawty) for her preſent and happy object? O thou ſoule. Whoſoevers thou art, and whereſoever thou art; O that thou wouldeſt ſeriouſly conſider, this thy laſt and beſt good, the very place and center of thy ſefe; conſider ſeriouſly, whether there can be any perfect happy place of reſt for thy ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides<note place="margin">Gen. 1. 27.</note> God? Art not thou made to the Image and likeneſſe of God? Then thy eſſentiall and totall dependency is from God, then thy totall inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and propenſion ought onely to be to God; Inquire into thy ſoule and aske whoſe Image it is, whoſe inſcription is ingraved therein? And thou ſhalt finde that it is only God, it is onely he that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2562:18"/> hath marked thee, and ſigned thee for himſelfe yea immediately for himſelfe. O the honours of intelligent creatures, by their inſtitution to have God only God, for their laſt, and immediate end, wherewith they muſt be eternally converſant; and to have him for the full and compleate object of their happineſſe, in the contemplation of whoſe beauty they muſt be eternally exerciſed. O the beſt of all beſt parts; for by participation, it is the<note place="margin">Mat. 25. 27. Luk. 10. 42. Pſa. 73 26</note> very joy of the Lord himſelfe; O chooſe this thou my ſoule, it ſhall never be taken from thee; the God of my heart and portion forever. O that my very <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>ſoule</hi> would exult and rejoyce after <hi>this living God</hi> for ever; O the ſweeteſt water ſprings; my ſoule, thirſt thou after them for ever. It is ſaid of thoſe, that love God ſincerely and make him the object of their hearts in this life,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 4. 7.</note> that they abide in God, and <hi>God in them;</hi> holily and graciouſly; O how joyous, holy, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious then in that glorious eſtate, ſhall our abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in God, and his abiding in us bee, to our ſoules for the dayes of his owne <hi>aeternity</hi> in himſelfe and our <hi>Coaeternity</hi> with himſelfe! But in this laſt end of man, and object of his happineſſe, we are to conſider, that which is obſervable in every object, to weet, in what formality or formall reſpect, God is found to be the object of mans happineſſe, and <hi>felicity;</hi> whether in the formality of goodneſſe,<note place="margin">To what for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall reſpect God is the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of mans happineſſe.</note> as he is infinitely good; or in the formality of <hi>power,</hi> as he is omnipotent; or of knowledge, as he is omniſcious; or of wiſdome, as he infinitely wiſe; or of truth, as he is infinitely cognoſcible and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2562:18"/> or <hi>justice,</hi> as he is infinitely juſt, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in his promiſes, and upright in his judgements mercifull in his rewards; or in the formality of any other of his attributes; <hi>vnity, ſimplicity, veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> &amp;c. Wherein (the obſervation and queſtion being novell and new) I had farre rather heare a maſter, then be a teacher my ſelfe. Sure I am, that the beautified and happy, <hi>ſee God in his owne very</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3 2.</note> 
                  <hi>preſence face to face,</hi> for ſo the beloved Diſciple (who ſucked this truth, from the breſt of truth) hath himſelfe pronounced: wee <hi>ſhall ſee him (ſaith</hi> hee) <hi>as hee is;</hi> not obſcurely as <hi>Timeus</hi> and <hi>Simoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plato in dialog.</note> Philoſophers: who both, being required to ſpeake what God was, the firſt anſwers onely by negation: ſhewing what God was not, but not what he was: the other the more he conſiders<note place="margin">God ſeene by the beatified as he is in him ſelfe.</note> God, the longer time he requires to anſwer the King what God was: but wee ſhall ſee him with eyes intuitive as he is in himſelfe. <hi>A moſt pure and perfect Act: all exiſtence and being:</hi> all eſſence and nature, and eſſentiall exiſtence, and Act moſt <hi>pure,</hi> without all manner of potentiallity, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection. And becauſe whatſoever is in God, is God: it cannot bee, but that hee who ſeeth God muſt needs ſee all that is in God: his <hi>power, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, wiſdome, bonity, purity, verity,</hi> which ſeeing, hee ſeeth them all to be the very deity and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head it ſelfe, wherewith he is unſpeakeably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted. But in what reſpect, is God formally the object of beautified Soules? That of God to<note place="margin">Exod. 33. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Moyſes, I will ſhew thee all good:</hi> may ſeeme to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, that God in the formality of the cheefeſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2562:19"/> good, is the object of mans happineſſe: That of <hi>Chriſt, This is aternall life, that they may know thee</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 17 3.</note> 
                  <hi>the onely true God,</hi> in the formality of <hi>unity</hi> and <hi>verity:</hi> that of <hi>St. Iohn, we ſhall ſee him</hi> as <hi>he is,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3. 2.</note> the formality of his infinite eſſence, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; that of the <hi>Apoſtle, face to face,</hi> under the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 12.</note> of <hi>Majesty</hi> and glory; ſo diverſly, ſeemes this truth to be delivered and diſtinguiſhed unto us; yet with reverence my imperfect meditation and apprehenſion telles me, If I miſconceave not, according to that of God to <hi>Moyſes, I will ſhew thee all good,</hi> that God under the formality of infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Exod. 33. 19.</note> good: good, as in <hi>power</hi> he is able to protect, <hi>wiſdom</hi> to <hi>direct, juſtice</hi> to guide and govern, boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty<note place="margin">God under the formality of good the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of mans happineſſe.</note> to enrich and ſatiate, but eſpecially as he is in every reſpect infinitely good in himſelfe, is the formall object of mans Felicity, and laſt Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And this is all that I can devoutly meditate or dare religiouſly affirme, of this unſpeakeable myſtery: whereinto to dive overcuriouſly, and to be a raſh ſearcher of <hi>majeſty,</hi> ſhould deſerve rather confuſion then illuſtration. <hi>Cherubins and Seraphins</hi> beholding the divine <hi>majeſty,</hi> out of a trembling re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence,<note place="margin">Iſa. 6. 2.</note> doe cover their faces: what ought wee then do who do dwell in houſes of clay? I ſhut<note place="margin">Iob. 4. 19.</note> up this poynt with this reverend note; <hi>An Alleluja,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 19. 1. 3.</note> a ſong of admiration beſeemes Gods <hi>majeſty</hi> in <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> above, but ſilence of admiration and devotion beſeemes Gods Sanctuary here on earth below, and yet not ſuch ſilence and admiration, as muſt be altogether ocious, and idle, as though man were in this life onely to conſider God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2562:19"/> in his creatures; for I underſtand that of <hi>Austen</hi> of a more cleare and perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to be had even in this life; though not ſo fully as in the next; <hi>Man was created,</hi> that he<note place="margin">Auguſt. de dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo Deo cap. 13.</note> might <hi>know his cheefest good God; knowing,</hi> might <hi>love him; loving</hi> him, <hi>might</hi> poſſeſſe him; <hi>poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> him, <hi>might enjoy him.</hi> For the further clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring whereof, we obſerve in our fourth Section.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>THE FOVRTH SECTION.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>God being the object of mans happineſſe, and his last end, it is ſhewed by what union, he is knitt, and united to the Soule, and thereby the Soule made happy.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe object of mans happineſſe, and his laſt end, being found to be <hi>God,</hi> onely <hi>God;</hi> it reſteth further to be conſidered, by what reall either union, or application, <hi>God</hi> is united to man, ſo that he doth enjoy <hi>God,</hi> as the preſent object of his happineſſe and laſt end. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in<note place="margin">Some glorious union neceſſary that the beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied may enioy God.</note> firſt moſt cleare it is, that ſome glorious uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is required for the ſame: for God being in all his creatures, high and lowe; Intelligent and unintelligent, Senſitive and ſenſeleſſe, in three generall ſorts and manners; To weet, by his<note place="margin">Three generall preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion of God in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> creatures.</note> 
                  <hi>exiſtence, preſence,</hi> and <hi>power;</hi> by his <hi>exiſtence,</hi> intimely and immediately coexiſting with them or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ather inexiſting in them: by his <hi>preſence,</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>mely
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2562:20"/> intimely beholding them, and every circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of them, with his all-ſeeing eyes: by his <hi>power,</hi> working in, with, and by them all; it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee (I ſay) but that <hi>God,</hi> being in the ſoules of the beatified, as the object of their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and laſt end; muſt needes bee in them, in a more peculiar ſort and manner, then he is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in all his other creatures. And this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous union, and application, muſt be by the meanes of ſome new glorious qualities, giftes or habits imparted to the beatified ſoules: for God being immutably, vnchangeably and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially<note place="margin">No change in God.</note> in himſelfe alwayes one &amp; the ſame and in the ſame manner (<hi>for with him there</hi> is no viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude<note place="margin">Iacob 1. 17.</note> or courſe of changing; being alwayes one, <hi>he is what he is</hi>) all the change that is, muſt be in<note place="margin">Exod. 3. 14.</note> the glorified and beatified Soules. Wherein if wee will arightly conſider, there is no repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy nor difficulty at all to be found. For as<note place="margin">God in a more ſpeciall ſort in the regenerate then he is in the unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Eph. 1. 6. Gala. 6 15. 2 Cor. 6 6. Apoc. 3. 20.</note> God is truely ſaid by the meanes of the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall gifts of <hi>faith, charity, grace</hi> and ſuch like, to be in the <hi>regenerate</hi> in a more peculiar ſort then he was in them, before thy were <hi>regenerated</hi> (for in the regenerate he <hi>walkes, Dwells,</hi> and feaſtes as in his houſes, temples, and <hi>Paradiſes</hi> of pleaſure, but on the unregenerate he looketh as yet diſtant from him;) So likewiſe <hi>God</hi> with, and in his <hi>glorified</hi> creatures in heaven; muſt needes bee vnited, in a more glorious and ſpeciall manner then he was united with them on earth, when they were onely <hi>regenerate,</hi> not as yet glorified. For the clearer underſtanding of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2562:20"/> which truth, wee are to make ſome ſpeciall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, and ſuppoſitions: * firſt I ſuppoſe, that this formal happineſſe, or immediate meanes<note place="margin">The glorious union can bee no extrinſecall thing.</note> thereof (which by a generall name I have called union) cannot be any extrinſecall thing, without the ſoules of the happy; For this union being required as a meanes for the attaining and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of God (which is extrinſecall, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſtent in reſpect of an infinite naturall diſtance to the ſoule,) if this union, ſhould be any thing that is extrinſecall to the ſoule; then ſhould there be required ſomewhat elſe to make it inherent and intrinſecall in the ſoule, or elſe wee muſt proceed into an infinity, untill wee ſhall finde ſomewhat inhaeſiue, and intrinſecall in the ſoule, whereby <hi>God</hi> may intimely be united unto the ſame. Againe, this union, and formall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">Formall happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe requires an inhaerent union.</note> maketh the beatified, happy not onely by imputation; but intrinſecally and moſt inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happy, and conſequently, the ſame muſt needs be inherent and in-exiſtent in their ſoules. For cleare it is, whatſoever thing is extrinſecall to another, as it maketh no reall impreſſion in it; ſo it cannot give any formall but onely an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecall<note place="margin">An extrinſecall cannot make a formall deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> inherent.</note> denomination unto it; by the way of improper denomination and imputation onely; which is no more nor no other, then a meere relation extrinſecall, and it cannot be otherwiſe. For, for example, how is it poſſible that for ſuch beauty which is without the face, and not in the face, the face ſhould be formally denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted beautifull? The denominations then, which
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2562:21"/> are of this kind extrinſecall, are like to the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations which are attributed to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing ſituate upon the right hand or left hand of the paſſenger, that goeth by it. According<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; if this formall happineſſe, ſhould not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haerently intrinſecally in the beatified ſoules, then ſhould they, not formally, but on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecally be denominated happy thereby; how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſhall they be found to be happy really, and in verity? Surely they ſhould be onely as really happy, by ſuch a manner of happineſſe, as a poore man may be really releeved by ſuch a manner of releefe, as <hi>St. Iames</hi> deſcribeth<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 2. 25. 16.</note> in his <hi>Epistle.</hi> I conclude then this point as moſt cleare, adding this reaſon further and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove: to weet, this formall happineſſe beeing a union, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is meerely impoſſible it ſhould bee ſuch, unleſſe it be found to be at laſt inhaerent i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on of the extreames, or parts, which are united<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which manner of inhaerency, cannot be in God, it muſt the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efore of neceſſity be in the glorified creature.<note place="margin">No <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall reall union poſſible betwixt G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d and his creatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> then perſona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, I ſuppoſe, that betwixt God, and any of his creatures, there is no other ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, reall and intrinſecall union poſſible, then that which is perſonall; which manner of union was truely ſound in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> whereby <hi>the Word</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh 1. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>was made fleſh,</hi> that is, ſubſiſtentially and perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally <hi>dwelt amongſt us, full of grace and truth, as the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>onely begotten Sonne of the Father.</hi> I ſay no other ſubſtantiall reall union poſſible, then that which is perſonall and ſubſtantiall: for by the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2562:21"/> very principles of Philoſophy it is moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that God cannot, neither as a ſubſtantiall part, be informed (as matter is) nor ſubſtantially informe (as the forme doth:) foreither of them to informe or to bee informed, includeth imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. Of which kind, in God who is a moſt pure and perfect eſſentiall act, there can be no ſort, nor degree at all. I am not ignorant, that ſome excellent witts, have affirmed; that Gods act of <hi>intellection</hi> and underſtanding, wherewith<note place="margin">Apud Captolum in 3. diſt. 14. 9. 1. et Greg. Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. in 1 diſt. 7. 9. art. 2. conclu. 3.</note> he beholdeth himſelfe, may bee, yea, and is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally united, unto the underſtandings and intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective parts of the beatified Soules; and that they by the very ſame act of intellection, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God beholdes himſelfe, do ſee and behold God, as he is in himſelfe; So that God and the Beatified, with one and the ſame <hi>iutellection,</hi> do behold God <hi>as he is in himſelfe:</hi> God beholding himſelfe, and comprehending himſelfe with an infinite action; but the beatified with the ſame infinite action, beholding and ſeeing him finitely and by participation onely.</p>
               <p>Theſe men, though they ſeeme to have many great reaſons, whereby they endeavour to ſhew ſuch an union to be as poſſible, as the union per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> or the union, that is face to face, in the beatified and bleſſed is; yet doubtleſſe they are greatly miſtaken, as by ſundry reaſons may appeare. As firſt thus; that if the very viſion and intellection of God were ſo united (as they dreame) to the ſoules of the beatified; yet they ſhould not therewith be able intuitively to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2562:22"/> ſee God, for it implyeth, that the power intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective<note place="margin">The beatified cannot ſee god by the ſame act of intellection and knowledge wherewith God ſeeth and beholdeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</note> of the ſoule, or the power volitive of the will of the Soule, ſhould know or underſtand; will or deſire, by any other actions, then ſuch as are efficiently from themſelves; which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out impiety cannot be affirmed of the intellecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God, as though it could be efficiently from them. To confirme this; An action vitall &amp; of life, doth eſſentially depend of a power of life; that power vitall which uſeth, it: and is and muſt alſo bee eſſentially immanent (if as an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) in the ſame power, which uſeth and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth it. Againe, it is not poſſible to declare, how the action of God, as an action, ſhould be united to the underſtanding power of the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified. Againe: how is it poſſible, for them to diſtinguiſh and ſhew, how the Beatified them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do ſee and behold God, in different de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of viſion, if they all ſee and behold him, with one and the ſame intellection; and yet moſt certeine it is that the Saints differ each from other in degrees of <hi>glory;</hi> as <hi>the ſtarres</hi> in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 41. 42.</note> do differ from each other in degrees of clarity. Againe, how is it poſſible that the Beatified, ſhould not comprehend God, by ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſmuch in God as God himſelfe doth, if they ſee and behold God, with the ſame viſion, &amp; intellection, wherewith God ſeeth and behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himſelfe? Againe, how ſhould the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the beatified, be onely a partaking and participation of Gods owne happineſſe, (as all the <hi>Ancients</hi> have affirmed, and <hi>Councells</hi> have
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2562:22"/> determined,) if one and the ſame action, ſhould be one and the ſame formall happineſſe of God, and the creatures? May wee not here apply to our purpoſe, thoſe words which the ſixth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Synod,</hi> uſed (in like caſe) againſt <hi>Eutyches? Neither will</hi> wee <hi>allow in</hi> any <hi>thing or reſpect,</hi> one and <hi>the ſame naturall operation of</hi> God, and <hi>the Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ature, that</hi> neither <hi>we may elevate that</hi> which is <hi>Created</hi> into <hi>the devine eſſence: neither depreſſe downe, that</hi> which is <hi>excellent</hi> in <hi>God, to the ſtate and condition of the creature.</hi> I conclude this point, affirming this opinion of theſe Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<note place="margin">An erronious opinion of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> to be ſo greatly againſt the glory and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of God, wherein they affirme that one and the ſame viſion of God, is the formall beatitude &amp; happineſſe both of God and of the creatures; that it is rather to be reputed an error, or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, then an opinion to be tolerated.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I ſuppoſe that the laſt felicity and happineſſe of man, muſt be ſo full and compleat, that it muſt beatifie, and make happy, the very nature of the ſoule, which is eſtentially life; and all the powers of the ſoule, which as powers of life are eſſentially vital, naturally apperteining to life, and eſſentially depending of, or emaning from the life of the ſoule: which being ſo, wee muſt of neceſſity find out, how or by what uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">The ſoules bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified muſt of neceſſity bee happy by ſome formall and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall actions and of her ſelfe</note> or guift the very ſoule in her owne nature, how and by what union or guift the very pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the ſoule, are in themſelves, immediately &amp; intimely united to God, &amp; thereby made hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. Touching the ſecond point, no doubt can
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2562:23"/> be made (for it is confeſſed by all) that the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall<note place="margin">converſant and exerciſed about God. Pſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. 10. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. 1. 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2. 5. 2 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. 13.</note> faculties, and powers of the ſoule, (to weet the will, underſtanding, and memory, are not onely united to God by glorious habites; to weet, the underſtanding by the light of wiſdome; the will with and by the light of glorified Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity (though it be the ſame eſſentially with the charity of this life) the memory with a glorious h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bitt of fruition for the tention and poſſeſſion of God in ſecurity; but further alſo that they are united to God, by their proper operations and actions; the underſtanding by a cleare vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion<note place="margin">By what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of actions the powers of the ſoule are conver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ant up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God.</note> and ſight of God; the will by a burning and ardent affection of the love of God; the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, by a joyous ruminating and recogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſecurity of her happineſſe in God. Theſe things (I ſay) are cleare, but the greateſt difficulty is, whether the ſoule her ſelfe, in her owne eſſence and nature be immediately united to God, or no: If ſo, then by what manner of gift or quality ſhe is ſo united. I call this the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt difficulty, not in reſpect of the thing it ſelfe, but in reſpect of the judgements of later <hi>Schoole-Divines;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A generall con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> of the Schoolemen.</note> who generally acknowledge, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther union, betwixt God and the ſoules beatifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſuch, as is by meanes of ſuch glorious habits, and qualities, which are immediately and ſubjectively in the powers of the ſoule; and by the meanes of ſuch actions, and operations, which the powers of the ſoule, enabled by ſuch glorious habits, do produce: I ſay, the point in it ſelfe is not difficult; nay rather, it is facill
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2562:23"/> and apparent.</p>
               <p>For firſt, how cleare is it, that God by a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious illapſe, and moſt in time preſence, is to be preſent to the beatified ſoules themſelves, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by<note place="margin">The ſoule her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately united to God, and not onely by her power, and the actions of them.</note> the ſoules, (who of themſelves are onely a naturall life) even as in this life by a gracious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation they become regenerate; ſo by a life glorious in the celeſtiall kingdome, they become glorious, and immortall: The life naturall, is onely an <hi>immortallity;</hi> the life gracious is an aſſecured <hi>ſanctity;</hi> the life glorious, though by participation, yet is a glorious <hi>coeternity</hi> of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance with <hi>immutability.</hi> Againe, cleare it is, that God, muſt be united, and gloriouſly united to the ſoule, and her powers; before ſhee can by her underſtanding ſee; by her will, love; by her memory embrace God. Now this unio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what elſe can it be, but a very ſtate of happineſſe? happineſſe and a very felicity in eſtate; even as happineſſe by viſion, actuall love, and delight, is happineſſe in exerciſe and operation. Againe, if there were no ſuch glorious inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ding illapſe, and inpreſence of God in the ſoule; but that all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall and glorious preſence of God, with the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atified ſoules, ſhould be onely by actions and opera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions; then this would follow; to weet, that the laſt happineſſe and felicity of the ſoules beatified, ſhould be immediatly from themſelves (for themſelves by their powers immediately do produce ſuch actions) and mediately onely from God, by the mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of thoſe glorious ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, which he onely infuſeth, and imparteth to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2562:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:2562:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:2562:25"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for thereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> happy. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>; to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> God, of the love of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God; are effectively <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the glorified powers and faculties of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> for theſe being both actions,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> or actions of life; and imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as actions, they muſt of neceſſity, be from the ſoule, whoſe actions they are: for it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> very terms, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as actions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> from any other powers then from theſe, whoſe actions they are. And as they are vitall actions, or actions of life, it alſo implyes contradiction, that as ſuch, they ſhould be from any other powers or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> then from ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vitall, and of life. Againe as actions immanent, they have eſſentiall, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, on the powers from which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are effectively.</p>
               <p>By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> is appa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, that the happineſſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> not (whatſoever Pope <hi>Benedictu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> have deſired and cert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n may have affirmed) onely and intimely, in the actions and operations of the beatified ſoules: For an eſtate perfect and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſummate, and a glorious grace of light, (whereby they are conjoyned to God, and enabled to ſee <hi>God,</hi> face to face: thereby to love him for himſelfe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2562:25"/> to delight in him as he is in himſelfe;) is ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and abſolutely required, that it is the very corner ſtone, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oundation, whereon all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt is built, and which doth thence from by neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry conſequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce follow. Againe, this may be thew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, by an argument, drawne from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, although the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> or would be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrongly; The laſt happineſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of that which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> happineſſe (which is God, onely G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> muſt of<note place="margin">Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> neceſſity, be immediately <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to that which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in man; to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to the very nature of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> man, yea formally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> wiſe done, then by a glorious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and change, made in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by grace, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmmate eſtate of participated <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> which is the foundation, and root of all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and loving, of, and in God; which the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in heaven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> St. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ter</hi> termes this an <hi>uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 5. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of Glory.</hi> And perhaps, of this, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> termes, the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, where he aſſumeth, that the<note place="margin">2 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:2562:26"/> followers of <hi>Chriſt, are changed into the ſame I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Chriſt, from glory to glory.</hi> This is the <hi>morning Starre</hi> which the Son of <hi>God</hi> hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed;<note place="margin">Reve. 2. 28.</note> to give unto them that hould faſt their faith, that overcome, and keepe his words unto the end. This is the <hi>white glorious robe,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thoſe, that ſtand before the Lambe and the<note place="margin">Reve. 7. 9.</note> throne, are cloathed and adorned. This is, that very <hi>glory of God, and light of the Lambe,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with<note place="margin">Reve. 21. 23.</note> the heavenly Citizens are ſo illuſtrated, that they need not, either light of the Sunne, or of the Moone. This is that very eſtate, place, or <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſion</hi> of participated <hi>eternity,</hi> which the Sonne of God promiſed to his diſciples, that he<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oh. 14. 2. 3.</note> went to provide for them; to weet, as it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in another place, that they ſhould <hi>walke</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reve. 3. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>with him in whites, for that they were worthy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</hi> This is that <hi>very Crowne of glory,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Saints of <hi>God</hi> in their very ſoules be crowned and inveſted, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe ſhal<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor 4. 17.</note> appeare in glory to beatifie and <hi>make happy all</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>oſſ. 3. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>thoſe that expect, and love his comming.</hi> And thus it is evidently ſhewed, that there is a glorious eſtate, and permanent glorious condition of the beatified in their very ſoules themſelves, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are intimely and immediately united to <hi>God:</hi> whereupon I make a fourth ſuppoſition.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, I ſuppoſe, that this glorious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and ſtate of the beatified, is not as a bedd of doune for ſleepe and reſt onely without any exerciſe or operation at all; no; it hath inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably joyned with, and inceſſantly emaning from
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2562:26"/> it, a moſt glorious exerciſe of the actions and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations<note place="margin">The eſtate of happineſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires that the ſoules of the beatified ſhould be in a continuall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified exerciſe of glorious actions</note> of every power and faculty of the ſoule: nay, it is impoſſible to conceive, how there ſhould be a glorious ſatiety of happineſſe, if there be not an inceſſant and never intermitted exerciſe of glorious operations, and a very ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of that glorious eſtate and condition of happineſſe, wherein the beatified are.</p>
               <p>This truely is moſt apparent. The <hi>Cherubins</hi> and <hi>Seraphins</hi> with inceſſant admiration, ſing the thrice <hi>holy, holy, holy,</hi> holy Lord <hi>God of Saboth.</hi> The ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> accounts all thoſe bleſſed, that dwell in the houſe of the Lord; <hi>for that they ſhall</hi> for all eternities bleſſe and ſing praiſes unto the Lord; Now theſe divine cries<note place="margin">Iſa. 6. 3.</note> and elevations of admiration, <hi>holy, holy, holy, Lord God of Sabboth,</hi> of the <hi>Cherubins</hi> and <hi>Seraphins;</hi> theſe praiſes and collaudations of the Saints; thoſe <hi>Alleluias,</hi> praiſe ye the Lord; praiſe ye the Lord, recounted by the <hi>Prophet</hi> in the <hi>Revelation;</hi> are they ought elſe? or can they be ought elſe? then thir ſeverall actions and operations of <hi>viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, love, joy, delight, reverence, admiration,</hi> which the <hi>Angells</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> ſeeing <hi>God,</hi> have with <hi>God,</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> and of <hi>God:</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> becauſe they are made partakers of the very joy of the Lord; in God becauſe they ſhall ſee him as he is of God, becauſe he is the eternall fountaine of light, ſtreaming into the ſoules and ſpirits of the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified; a moſt glorious light whereby they ſee God and his glorious <hi>Majesty</hi> moſt clearely: and conſequently they cannot but <hi>love</hi> him, but <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:2562:27"/> in him; admire, reverence, and adore him; <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> him, thereby acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging him for the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all creatures whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> above, or on the earth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> within the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arth beneath.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, I ſuppoſe that this glorious exerciſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> glorious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> God. Some there are, who do thinke, that there is in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an abſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive knowledge of <hi>God</hi> by his creatures, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> an anſwerable love ariſing from the ſame, but without all queſtion they are herein miſtaken for ſeeing the knowledges of <hi>God</hi> by<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 13.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> as being obſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, in part, and imperfect, and of <hi>God</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are to cauſe, and to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> when as the cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tuitive viſion of him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> given unto the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tified; why then ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>God</hi> by and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ough his creatures when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall be <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> is in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> whenas, he ſhall <hi>be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> whenas we <hi>ſhall k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>w <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> even as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> not obſeurely in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> clearely, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> face to face. By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> viſion, the ſpirits and ſoules of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſo ſwallowed up, that the pretended abſtractive knowledge of <hi>God,</hi> by, and in his creatures, ſhall be altogether needleſſe, yea perhaps impoſſible, if we would ſtand longer to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame. And ſo I come more ſpecially to diſtinguiſh the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2562:27"/> principall actions and operations, which the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atified have in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> God.</p>
               <p>The firſt and paine action of the beatified, about and on God the fountaine of all the reſt) is a cleare and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> viſion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him, <hi>as he is in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>himſelfe.</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, with God before God and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> preſence of God: thereby not onely<note place="margin">The firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the beatified.</note> ſeeing that which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nifeſt of God, in regard of his creatures, but alſo that which is manifeſt of God in himſelfe, by his owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſential light; <hi>For God is light, and in him there is no dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe at all:</hi> And by this intuitive viſion of God,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> the beatified ſpirits ſo ſee God (their intellective powers being enabled thereunto by the light of glory) that their powers are thereby fully ſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and at reſt; moſt ſweetely and joyouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying that, which God promiſed to <hi>Moyſes; I will ſhew thee all good.</hi> Out of this preſentiall and<note place="margin">Exod. 33. 19.</note> intuitive viſion of good, all good clearly beheld, there followeth neceſſarily a double love of <hi>God:</hi> I ſaid neceſſarily; for it is impoſſible, that good,<note place="margin">Second glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous action.</note> all good, eſſentially good, having no evill in it; ſhould clearely bee propoſed to the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and that the will (whoſe proper and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall object is good) ſhould not love and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the ſame. Now this love, is a double ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, or embracing of the ſoule, into, and of that infinite goodneſſe which is in God; firſt of that infinite goodneſſe of God as he is good in himſelfe, goodneſſe it ſelfe; ſecondly, of the very ſame goodneſſe of God as by participation it is imparted, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated, (as their laſt end
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2562:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:2562:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:2562:29"/> and finall good) unto the ſoules and ſpirits of the Beatified. This with reverence I preſume to declare by that which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> delivereth in his Epiſtleto the <hi>Corinthians:</hi> to weet, <hi>that love never fadeth away;</hi> whereby it is moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 8.</note> that the <hi>love</hi> of the regenerate in this life, &amp; the <hi>love</hi> of the beatified, in the life of bliſſe and glory, is one and the ſame eſſentially and in nature; the onely diverſity is, that by an exceſſe of perfection, that of the beatified doth excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly ſurpaſſe, that which is of the Pilgrimes in this valley of <hi>mortality.</hi> If then the love of the Elect, whilſt they are in the way, abſent from God; and the love of the Elect, when they are in their country, and at their end preſent with God, be one and the ſame; then muſt it needs follow, that as the love of the Elect in the way, tendeth with a double reſpect to God, to love<note place="margin">A double kind of glorious love.</note> 
                  <hi>God</hi> as he is good in himſelfe, and to himſelfe, (which is the love of friendſhip and amity) and to love him, as he is good to his elect, their to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and finall good (which is a love of a holy and ſacred concupiſcence) ſo likewiſe the love of <hi>God</hi> in the beatified inclineth them to love <hi>God</hi> as hee is good to himſelfe, and in himſelfe, and as he is moſt graciously good unto themſelves: And can there be made any doubt of this? what? ſhall the habit of <hi>love &amp; charity</hi> moove &amp; incline us moſt divinely to love God, in both reſpects, as he is obſcurely ſeene by faith, whileſt wee are <hi>Pilgrims</hi> and travellers in this mortall life? and ſhall not the ſame habitt of <hi>love</hi> and <hi>charity;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2562:29"/> now perfected and glorious, neceſſarily and inevi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ably moove us, to love God in both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, for his goodneſſe as it is infinitely in himſelfe, and for his goodneſſe it as it is; and as he is by participation communicated unto us. Yea, this is ſo apparent, that the man <hi>according to Gods owne heart,</hi> profeſſes what his love was in this life of mortality, and what he longed for, and longed after, in that life of glory and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, thus; <hi>What is there,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for me in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 73. 25. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>beſides thee;</hi> and beſides thee, what would I <hi>upon earth, the God of my heart and of my ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and my portion for ever?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vpon and out of this double love of the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite goodneſſe of God, both as it is in himſelfe eſſentially himſelfe, and to his elect by participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (not now abſent from them, but moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely preſent with them) there ariſeth a double<note place="margin">A double glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ioy.</note> joy and gladneſſe; joy to ſee God, whom they ſo dearely love, infinitely good and happy in himſelfe; joy to ſee themſelves, in full and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure poſſeſſion of that infinite good as their laſt end, and the compleat object of their happineſſe. This joy is that wherof <hi>Auguſtine</hi> very excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently. <hi>There is a joy which is not graunted to the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. 9. Confeſſe.</note> 
                  <hi>wicked, but to thoſe who worſhip</hi> thee <hi>freely, whoſe joy thou thy ſelfe art, and that is, the very</hi> life <hi>of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, to joy in thee, and for thee, that is the bleſſed life, and there is no other.</hi> Of this we are to underſtand thoſe joyous words of <hi>Chriſt; Welcome; well done good and faithfull ſervants,</hi> you have <hi>beene faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 25. 21 24.</note> 
                  <hi>in a</hi> little, <hi>I will make</hi> you <hi>rulers over much: en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2562:30"/> thy Maſters joy.</hi> Loe, the Maſter of this joyous feaſt, calls his owne joy the joy of his faithfull ſervants; which is ſo great, and ſo ſurpaſſing, that holy <hi>David</hi> dareth thus by a familiar metaphore to expreſſe the exceeding ſweetneſſe of the ſame. <hi>They ſhall be ſatiated</hi> (he ſpeakes of the <hi>Beatified) with an over plentifullneſſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 36. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>of thy houſe, and with a torrent or river of thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, thou ſhalt inebriate them and make them dronke.</hi> O moſt dviine <hi>ſatiety,</hi> O moſt ſacred inebriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the beatified ſoules (<hi>Seeing, loving, delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; enjoying</hi> God) of <hi>love,</hi> of <hi>adoration,</hi> of <hi>admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> of <hi>aſtoniſhment,</hi> of <hi>content,</hi> of <hi>ſatiety,</hi> of <hi>reſt,</hi> of <hi>delight,</hi> of <hi>joy,</hi> of <hi>enjoying.</hi> O bleſſed Spirits, O Beatified Soules, ſo ſatiated, ſo inebriated, that ſeeing and admiring they cannot but admire at, and delight in, ſo infinitely good, ſo infinitely ſweet, ſo infinitely joyous a <hi>good.</hi> Holy <hi>David</hi> conſidering the ſame, could not but with an eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Spirit cry out, <hi>O how amiable</hi> are thy dwelings<note place="margin">Pſal. 84. 1. 2.</note> thou Lord of hoſts! <hi>my ſoule longeth and fainteth after the Courts of the Lord. Bernard</hi> moſt ſweetly; <hi>The ſweet aboundance of that houſe,</hi> and the <hi>Torrent</hi> of that pleaſure, <hi>neither</hi> eye <hi>hath</hi> ſeene, <hi>or eare heard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bernard in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat. ſerm: 4.</note> 
                  <hi>nor the heart of man hath conceived. Doe not thinke therefore O man, to</hi> heare that <hi>which the eare of man hath not heard; neither ſeeke thou of man, to know what that is, which the eye of man hath not</hi> ſeene, <hi>nor the minde of man hath conceived;</hi> Let us <hi>rather manfully and couragiouſly labour in theſe our taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, that in the end, we may be gloriouſly glorified, in the houſe of Gods</hi> bliſſe <hi>and glory above, and be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2562:30"/> made partakers of that joy, which ſhall never fade, nor fall away; which ſhall be ſuch as it ſhall fully ſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, and yet never cloy; ever be had, or enjoyed; and yet ever be deſired: not with anxiety after more or other, but with a moſt aſſured continuance of the ſame. Againe thereof Auſtine</hi> very divinely. <hi>There ſhall be what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall bee worthy of</hi> love, <hi>neither ſhall any thing</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auſtine his 12. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>itate.</note> 
                  <hi>be deſired, which ſhall not bee there; all that ſhall be there, ſhall be good, and the ſupreame God, ſhall be the ſoveraigne good, and moſt happy it ſhall be to knowe, and to be aſſecured, that that good ſhall ever be. There ſhall wee be at reſt and ſee thee; there ſhall we ſee and love thee, wee ſhall love and prayſe thee, which ſhalt bee our end without end. For what other is our end, than to come to a kingdome, which hath no end? thus he. Beſides the above expreſſed actions, and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the beatified ſoules and ſpirits, I doe obſerve another,</hi> which I call a retention or <hi>holding</hi> or poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of God, which whether it be all theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions together, as they are exerciſed upon God ſo intimely, and gloriouſly <hi>preſent;</hi> or whether there be beſids them another action of <hi>conquieſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> and reſting in, and upon God, as the laſt and compleat end of the beatified, it is not eaſie to diſtinguiſh. Sure I am, that ſuch a reſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſcency there is, the which in all humility and modeſty I will endeavour to difference and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh; and O moſt happy my <hi>Soule,</hi> when I ſhall come, clearely to behould, and know the ſame. O <hi>how</hi> with the very heartſtrings of my <hi>ſoule, do I not onely deſire but long after the ſame! O the</hi> God <hi>of my heart, my Soule longeth after</hi> thee, to ſee
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2562:31"/> 
                  <hi>thee,</hi> 'O love thee, to delight in thee, and to live and reſt in thee and by thee, for ever and ever. O fill and repleniſh my Soule here ſo to feare thee, that in the end I may attaine thee to enjoy thee; Amen. It cannot have beene uathought of by any, who have arightly thought of their laſt end, and of that happineſſe, which is layed <hi>up for all</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>theſe that love God and his comming;</hi> but that they have in their ſoules conceived a living hope, and fervent deſire of attaining unto the ſame. We glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, ſaith St. <hi>Paul, in the hope of glory of the ſonnes</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>of God. Iob</hi> laid up in his breaſt, as a moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious jewell, the hope that he had, that he ſhould <hi>by himſelfe ſee God his redeemer and Saviour.</hi> We are<note place="margin">Iob. 19. 27. Heb. 10. 23.</note> all <hi>encouraged to hould fast the confeſsion of our hope, a hope firme and unmooveable.</hi> The <hi>Apostle</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired<note place="margin">Phi 1. 23.</note> to be <hi>diſſolved, and to be with Christ.</hi> And what faithfull ſoule is there, who longeth not for, and deſires not after the comming of the Lord; that he may enjoy that crowne <hi>of glory and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>which God hath laid up for all thoſe that love his comming?</hi> Now this hope of the laſt happineſſe and longing after the ſame, if it be arightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, will be found according to the doctrine of all ſound Divines, to be ſpecially an action or affection of the will of man (enabled and illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by grace) tending to and longing after God abſent: which affection of hope and deſire, ceaſeth not, untill the good that is deſired and hoped for, is obteined, and made preſent; but the good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had and attained unto, then the affection of hope ceaſeth, for what we have and injoy, we hope
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2562:31"/> not for, nor long after; That <hi>which a man ſeeth (that is,</hi> as I interpret him, ſeeth and by ſight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeth) <hi>how can he hope</hi> for, ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 24. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Auſten</hi> excellently, <hi>Hope is a child of faith, by which</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt de ſpirit. et lit.</note> 
                  <hi>man hopeth (from him whom he knoweth,) for that</hi> which he yet hath not; which hope, being in this ſtate the expectation of an <hi>immortall</hi> life, I do fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call it, the very <hi>life of this our mortall life;</hi> the which (though fortune often failes) will never faile, nor in the end deceave the upright and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent. Who, becauſe by hope he waiteth <hi>on God,</hi> and hath his heart repoſed upon God, as <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 13. 35.</note> had hers, is as confident as a <hi>lion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now when as theſe affections of <hi>hope</hi> and <hi>deſire,</hi> by reaſon that the good which was hoped for, is obteined, doth end and ceaſe, there muſt needes<note place="margin">Some glorious action of the will muſt needs ſucceed in roome of the action of hope.</note> in lieu and place of theſe former, ſucceede and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, ſome other action and affection of the will, which formally and reſpectively, muſt anſwere unto the former; The former was hope to; this muſt be a tention and poſſeſſion: the former was deſire after, this muſt be uſe; the former was lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging after, this muſt be fruition and injoying; the former was tending to the good, to attaine it; this a tention, reſt, and conquieſcency in the good at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. The motion of the ſtone to the center, and the reſting of the ſtone at, or ſo neere the center as poſſibly it may, is like the hope or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; and tention or poſſeſſion of man to and in its laſt end. Now as the motion of the ſtone to, and the reſt of the ſtone in or at the center, ariſeth from, and is agreeing to, the naturall inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2562:32"/> the ſtone hath to its center; ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the deliberate hope, deſire, or inclination whether naturall and rationall, and ſapientiall, and ſupernaturall, of the ſoule and bleſſed ſpirits to their laſt end: whether naturall or ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and their reſt and conquieſcency in the ſame, is from one, and the ſame faculty of the ſoule, to weet, the will: whether naturally (if to her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall end) or ſupernaturally (if to her ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall end) <hi>ſhee bee enabled,</hi> ſtrengthened, and illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the ſame.</p>
               <p>And although it falleth out often, that the ſame faculty which inclines to good things, doth not alwayes by it ſelfe attaine and apprehend the ſaid good things, but they are attained and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, by ſome other powers; yet the ſame power and faculty, that deſires them, and inclines to them, doth reſt in them, and delight in them, being had and attained. For example, the heart of man deſires ſome rich treaſure of Iewell (for<note place="margin">Matt. 6. 21.</note> where the treaſure is there is the heart alſo, ſaith our <hi>Saviour</hi>) and yet the hand, and other powers of man take immediate poſſeſſion and apprehend the ſame: n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vertheleſſe the ſame being attained, the heart or appetite of man, takes content, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and reſt in the Iewell, or treaſure obtained. So likewiſe the will of man is that, which enclines whole man, either naturally by her naturall force to ſome naturall good; or ſupernaturally, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of Grace ſupernaturall and ſapientiall, to her laſt end and happineſſe; But the attaining and apprehenſion thereof, is by the cleare viſion,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2562:32"/> and fervent love of God, as he is in himſelfe. And yet nevertheleſſe, the eternall reſt, repoſe, and conquieſcency (which I call <hi>fruition</hi>) in the ſame God, ſo clearely and intuitively ſceene, ſo ſweetely beloved; is immediately from, in, and of the glorified will, whoſe proper action as it is to deſire and hope for: ſo it is eternally to reſt and repoſe herſelfe and all other faculties of the ſoule, yea the ſoule herſelfe in the laſt end of her happineſſe, and her cheefeſt and onely good: So that it is ſhee that commands <hi>this conquieſcency</hi> and reſt unto hereſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be turned O my ſoule into</hi> thy reſt! For the<note place="margin">Pſa. 116. 7.</note> Lord hath done well for thee: It is ſhee that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ults; <hi>This is my reſt, here will I abide for ever</hi> This is<note place="margin">Pſa. 132. 14.</note> my <hi>joy</hi> which no power ſhall take from me: This, this is that <hi>eternall rest</hi> and conquieſcency which the <hi>Apostle</hi> adviſeth us ſo ſervently to purſue:<note place="margin">Heb. 4. 10. 11.</note> This is that happy and moſt ſweet repoſe which the reſtleſſe <hi>Ambitious, Avaricious, Preſumptuous, Contentious, Blaſphemous, Luxurious, perjurious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> ſhall never injoy: For as it is in the Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>They ſhall have no reſt neither day</hi> nor <hi>night, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 4. 1. &amp; 14. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>they ſerve ſuch Gods in their</hi> workes (although they may have tongues and lookes as Angells of light) Gods their owne luſts, which <hi>ſhall give</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 16. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>them no reſt neither day nor night.</hi> On that ſuch wretched ſoules (who imitating <hi>Satan,</hi> ſeeke reſt in ſuch drye places of <hi>Pride, Avarice, periury, Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy) returning into themſelves,</hi> and repenting them of their manifold tranſgreſſions (<hi>whether by their walking in the counſell</hi> of the <hi>ungodly, or ſtanding
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2562:33"/> in the way of</hi> ſinners, or ſitting on the <hi>chayres of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 1.</note> the pernicious ſcorners) would endeavour for<note place="margin">Pſa 95. 11.</note> that reſt which God <hi>hath ſworne he would never give to thoſe who haue hardened their hearts against his calls!</hi> And will he then give it to thoſe who ſhall willingly and deliberately either for <hi>gaine</hi> or envy forſweare themſelves, and abjure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of his protection, <hi>So helpe</hi> us <hi>God ſo helpe us God?</hi> O the moſt fearefull and execrable evill of perjury, of Elder and of Latter times! That worthy Cardinall of Cambrey <hi>Peter</hi> de <hi>Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aco,</hi> hath a fearefull ſaying touching the coruption of the Popiſh church of his times (to weet, at and about the time of the Councell of <hi>Conſtance) That the Church was come to that paſſe, that ſhee was worthy to be ruled and governed by reprobates:</hi> which his ſaying may we not interpret in reſpect of moſt fearefully Blaſpheming the Majeſtie of heaven, by moſt execrable falſe <hi>oathes</hi> and <hi>perjuryes?</hi> And ſurely who may or can be reputed to ſinne more fearefully, than thoſe who by falſe <hi>oathes</hi> and <hi>perjuries</hi> do willingly and premeditatly put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of Gods protection? If they who<note place="margin">Matt. 10. 33.</note> ſhall deny <hi>God before men ſhall be denyed of him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Angells?</hi> what ſhall or can become of them who ſhall deliberately abjure him before men? But to returne to our purpoſe touching the reſt and repoſe of the ſoule in God and his Graces; <hi>Peeter</hi> upon the mount no ſooner beheld the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious<note place="margin">Matt. 17. 4.</note> transfigured body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but he cryes out with a moſt fervent longing deſire of, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in that object; <hi>Let us make here</hi> (ſaith he to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2562:33"/> 
                  <hi>Chriſt) three tabernacles; one for thee, a ſecond for Elias, a third for Moyſes;</hi> So naturall it is, for the will, to reſt and content herſelfe in <hi>Good</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, apprehended by the underſtanding as <hi>Good;</hi> that it is impoſſible, that the will ſhould not, according to the meaſure of the <hi>Good,</hi> take content therein; How then is it imaginable or poſſible, but that <hi>God</hi> infinitely <hi>good,</hi> being as ſuch propoſed to the will (beloved dearely, and enjoyed happily) but that the will poſſeſſed with ſuch a ſweet trinity, of <hi>ſight, love, and joy;</hi> ſhould (ſolacing her owne ſoule with infinite content) thus crie out to her ſelfe, <hi>This is my reſt; here</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 132. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>will I dwell, and abide for ever?</hi> The heart of man, is reſtleſſe, till it come to its laſt end, which being once attayned, her aeternall reſt is a verie banket of unſpeakeable joy and peace. <hi>S. Auſten</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. 1. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe.</note> verie worthily; <hi>Thou haſt made us O Lord for thy ſelfe,</hi> and <hi>reſtleſſe are our hearts, till they come unto thee:</hi> But when they are come, their reſt is a ſupper of everlaſting ſweetnes; the which, my meditation could affoord to call, a celeſtiall and divine ſatiety, of a never ſatiated ſoule, and a ſupernall inebriation of glory, whereby the ſoules beatified, and all their powers, and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes of them, are filled with ſo great a iucundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as it is poſſible for them to attayne to; and ſo are therewith moſt divinely ſatiated. The Royall Prophet, of this glorious banquet profeſſes and<note place="margin">Pſal. 17. 15.</note> ſingeth thus, <hi>I ſhall be filled, and ſatiated, when thy glory ſhall appeare. S. Auſten</hi> hereof moſt<note place="margin">Auguſt. tract. 3. in Ioh.</note> ſweetely: <hi>Such ſhall bee that delight of beautie; that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2562:34"/> it ſhall be alwayes preſent with thee, and yet thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſatiated; or rather thus; that thou maiſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſatiated, and yet never ſatiated: for if I ſhall ſay that thou ſhalt not be ſatiated; there ſhall be a hunger and thirſt: if I ſhall ſay, thou ſhalt bee ſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then wilt thou feare a cloying there; where ſhall bee neyther famine, hunger, nor thirſt, nor any tedious cloying, not then ſhall I ſay? I know not; God hath that, which he will beſtowe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo concluding this poynte, not having more what to ſay, of the ſweetneſſe of this ſweetnes; of the unſatiadnes of this ſatiety, of the iucundity of this eternall reſt; I pray, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech <hi>God</hi> of his infinite mercy, that he wil be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to conduct my Soule, and the Soules of all the devout and faythfull readers hereof, to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of <hi>rest,</hi> and heaven of <hi>Satietie.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>FIFTH SECTION.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein is more particularly handled, in what action, or actions, the laſt happineſſe of man, doth ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſiſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe principall actions, of the laſt happines of man, being thus diſtinguiſhed: I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve firſt, that if a man would imitate the ſchool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the <hi>Thomiſts and Scotiſts;</hi> then were he to diſtinguiſh, wherein, and in what action for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally and principally, the ſame happines doth conſiſt: The learned cannot bee ignorant, what fervent diſputes there are, betwixt the <hi>Scotiſts
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2562:34"/> and Thomiſts</hi> on this poynt; the former giving the ſame unto the act of the will, the other, unto the act of the underſtanding; which their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion eyther ſyde endeavours, by ſundry reaſons to prove and confirme; but in my opinion, they toſſe <hi>Siſiphus his stone, they labour in vayne;</hi> for what neede they, with the quinteſſence of their witts, to refine and diſtinguiſh farther, than the holy ſcriptures have done? Who is ignorant, that hath read the ſcriptures, but that the laſt happines of man, as it is ſometimes called the <hi>joy of the Lord,</hi> whereby the will (the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate<note place="margin">Mat. 25. 21. 25.</note> ſubject and Efficient of joy) ſeemes to have the preeminency; ſo elſewhere, they pronounce <hi>life everlasting,</hi> to conſiſt in <hi>the knowledge of God: This is life everlasting,</hi> that they <hi>may know thee, to be the only true God; and whome thou hast ſent Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Like obſervations I might make of other paſſages of ſcripture; but the pointe is cleare, that in the Phraſe of holy Scripture, the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and felicity of man, doth conſiſt, in all thoſe integrall partes, which hee attributes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: to weet, cleare and intuitive <hi>Viſion, Love, Ioy, Delight, Peace, Rest, Eternall Prayſing, &amp; Adoringe</hi> of God with ſuch like, by which it is cleare that in the ſenſe and intent of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the laſt happineſſe of man (to uſe <hi>Boetius,</hi> his<note place="margin">Boetius l. 3. de conſolat.</note> phraſe,) <hi>is a ſtate perfect with a confluence of all that is good;</hi> but wherein formally it doth conſiſt, or what is the principall action thereof, it doth not expreſſe; and therefore herein, I require mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty in the <hi>ſchoolemen;</hi> and I would to God that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2562:35"/> in like controverſies, all men (which would bring great peace to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi>) would imitate and expreſſe ſuch modeſty as is requiſite; but there is no hope of amendment. I cannot therefore, but here lament that arrogant and itching reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſenes of ſome witts, and in none more appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent than in the <hi>Pope and Tridentine ſages,</hi> with the ſtatizing <hi>Ignatians;</hi> who in not unlike con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, by teaching and preaching; by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeing and comaunding; what is <hi>formall,</hi> what is <hi>materiall;</hi> what is <hi>principall,</hi> what is <hi>Secondary,</hi> have formally, if not overturned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> at leaſt ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and diſioynted, many of the churches of <hi>God.</hi> O yee that are <hi>Traditioniſts;</hi> And O wee, that worthily embrace nothing for <hi>fayth,</hi> but what the holy ſcriptures have recommended unto us: O doe not yee; nor let not any of us, diſioyne and ſeparate <hi>thoſe</hi> thinges which <hi>God</hi> hath joyned together; O let us, with a religious reverence, uſe the verie phraſe of holy ſcriptures; where they attribute to any action or operation a <hi>principall concurrence;</hi> let not us deny it: where they graunt <hi>a neceſſarie concurrence,</hi> let us graunt it; where they require <hi>a neceſſarie concurrence, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, or ſociety</hi> of many actions to ſalvation; let us teach the ſame. O let us feare that curſe which is threatned againſt thoſe <hi>that ſhall eyther</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reve. 22. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>adde or diminiſh, to, or from the ſacred word of God.</hi> But to returne to our purpoſe which wee have now in hand.</p>
               <p>If nothing, can truly and ſolidly bee affirmed of the laſt happineſſe, and gloriouſe felicity of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2562:35"/> man, beſydes that which the word o<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <hi>God</hi> hath revealed, from the boſome of the <hi>Father;</hi> and all that which indeed is revealed, doth onely (not ſpeaking of the formality of any action more then other) declare unto us, that the ſame hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, is a <hi>ſumme</hi> of all good things; a <hi>Confluence</hi> of all <hi>Ioy and Peace,</hi> and other ſuch exellent things,<note place="margin">Iſa. 64. 1 Cor. 2 9.</note> 
                  <hi>as eye hath not ſeene, eare hath not heard, nor the heart of man hath conceaved; then undoubtedly</hi> (if we would arightly diſtinguiſh) wee ſhould rather confeſſe our owne ignorance therein; than overboldly and arrogantly to confine the forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the ſame, rather to the actions of the wil, then to thoſe of the underſtanding, or to theſe of the underſtanding rather then to thoſe of the will. <hi>S. Auſten</hi> excellently, <hi>That which God hath</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt: lib. 22. de Civi.</note> 
                  <hi>prepared for thoſe that love him, is not apprehended by fayth, is not attayned by hope, and is not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by Charity: It ſurpaſſeth thoſe deſires and wiſhes; it may bee gotten and acquired, but it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee fully eſteemed or prized:</hi> And ſo not daring peremptorily to affirme, wherein only (and in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe) the formality of the ſame doth conſiſt, I conclude this obſervation with the ſweete ſaying of venerable <hi>Cyprian. The Saynts, ſhall all</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cyprian de lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Marty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll.</note> 
                  <hi>rejoyce in glory, they ſhall ſee God, and they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in him; they ſhall be glad, and delighted; they ſhall flowe in glory, and be jocound with an aeternall felicity; There they ſhall not only tast how ſweet God is, but they ſhall be filled and ſatiated with a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſweetnes; nothing ſhall be wanting to them; yet nothing that is hurtefull, with them; Chriſt preſent
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2562:36"/> ſhall fill and ſatiate everye deſire of them; they ſhall not waxe ould, they ſhall not languiſh, they ſhall not rott; A perpetuall ſanitye, a happy aeternity, ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the ſufficiency of that happineſſe; there ſhall be no concupiſcence in the members; there ſhall ariſe noe rebellion of the fleſh; but the whole ſtate of man, ſhall be chaste and peaceable; laſt of all, God ſhall be all in all, his preſence ſhall fill and ſatiate, all the powers and facultyes, both of body and mind: all needfull ſervice and miniſtration of Angells ſhall ceaſe; the whole City, being filled and arightly ordered; the ſtate of this conſummate happineſſe, ſhall neyther bee inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, nor chaunged: Thus hee with many</hi> more excellent prayſes of that glory, and yet hee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth not, the leaſt part of the excellent joyes, which ſhall be injoyed there: for to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> this poynte in <hi>Auſtens</hi> phraſe, <hi>VVee maye more eaſily ſhew, what is not there, then what is there;</hi> wee may more eaſily declare, what ill is not there; then expreſſe, the gloriouſe emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of all <hi>good, that is there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though I dare not diſtinguiſh peremptorily, with eyther Sect of the <hi>Schoolemen,</hi> wherein the formality of mans happineſſe doth conſiſt; yet wee may not deny, but that in that moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſe eſtate; three gloriouſe <hi>Actions,</hi> are moſt ſpecially recommended and ſpoken of by the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> to witt, <hi>Viſion, Dilection, and Ioye, or Fruition;</hi> which three, certeyne ſchoolmen call<note place="margin">A miſtake of the ſchoolmen. What is the dowrie of the beatified.</note> the dowrie of the <hi>Beatified</hi> Spirits; but they are undoubtedly miſtaken: for as in carnall mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, the dowrie which eyther the Parents of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2562:36"/> the <hi>Bride,</hi> doe give; that the husband may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter undergoe the charges and burden of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; or which the <hi>Bridegroome</hi> maye give out of exceſſe of love to pleaſe and honour the <hi>Bride;</hi> are not actions, nor operations; but gifts of <hi>Iewells, Ornaments, Moneyes</hi> or ſuch like: ſo likewiſe in that gloriouſe <hi>Marriage</hi> above, when the <hi>Lambe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 19. 7.</note> and his <hi>Spouſeſſe</hi> are knitt togeather, in the linke or wedding-ring of a gloriouſe <hi>aeternitye,</hi> the dowrie is not operations and actions (for thoſe are the verie exerciſe, fruition, and conſummation (if I may ſo write) of the gloriouſe marriage it ſelfe. But they are gloriouſe <hi>Habitts, Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> and <hi>Iewells</hi> of the Soules of the <hi>Bride;</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led<note place="margin">Pſal. 36. 10.</note> by holy <hi>David,</hi> the light wherewith <hi>God</hi> is to be <hi>ſeene;</hi> by the <hi>Prophet</hi> in his Revelation, <hi>The</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 21. 11. and 19 8.</note> 
                  <hi>brightnes of God and his light:</hi> agayne, <hi>fine white</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 6. 11. 2. Timoth. 4. 8. 1. Pet. 6. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>ſilke,</hi> wherewith the <hi>ſpouſeſſe</hi> is to adorne herſelfe; agayne, <hi>white ſtoles,</hi> wherewith the beatified Soules are to bee adorned and honnoured: and the Scriptures elſewhere, call them <hi>crownes</hi> of glory, <hi>names written in the foreheades,</hi> of the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, <hi>Thrones of glory,</hi> with many ſuch like glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious epethites.</p>
               <p>So then, the gloriouſe actions of the beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, are not the <hi>dowrie</hi> it ſelfe, but ſuppoſe a <hi>dowrie,</hi> which to expreſſe, wants not great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty; yet if I bee not miſtaken, as for the act of <hi>Viſion,</hi> there is required a gloriouſe habitt of the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>glory,</hi> ſo likewiſe for the act of <hi>Love,</hi> a gloriouſe habitt of <hi>glorified Charity;</hi> for the act of <hi>Ioy</hi> and <hi>fruition,</hi> a gloriouſe habitt, anſwering
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2562:37"/> to the habitt of <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Deſire:</hi> And theſe, if I be not miſtaken, are that <hi>ſplendent ſilke,</hi> thoſe <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſe whites,</hi> thoſe <hi>new-names,</hi> thoſe <hi>ſeates and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reve. 3. 4. 12. 21. et 6. 11. et 7. 9. et 19. 14. et 21. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>thrones of glory,</hi> thoſe <hi>glorified ſtoles, that clarity and brightnes of God,</hi> whereof the holy Prophet makes ſo cleare, and expreſſe mention. And in truth, the dowrie of the beatified <hi>Spirits</hi> and Soules can be no other, then that glorious <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurye</hi> of glorious ornaments, <hi>graces,</hi> and gifts, whereby they are prepared and fitted, for the <hi>wedding</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the marriage of the <hi>Lambe:</hi> and whereby they are enabled, to all thoſe glorious actions, and operations; in which, as the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious iſſue, and <hi>offspring</hi> of that <hi>Marriage,</hi> they are for all <hi>aeternities,</hi> inceſſantly and joyouſly, to exerciſe, and there with to ſolace themſelves, in the preſent viſion and fruition of God.</p>
               <p>This ſtate being ſuch and ſo glorious, it were idle, with the <hi>ſchoolemen</hi> to inquire, whether in<note place="margin">An idle queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of lome ſchoole-men.</note> ſuch a ſtate be required a rectitude, and upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the will, or not; For how is it poſſible but that there ſhould be a <hi>rectitude</hi> of the will,<note place="margin">True happines cannot be with out a rectitude of the will.</note> when as there is ſuch a cleare intuitive viſion of all good, ſo fully injoyed and poſſeſſed? Is not the wil of herſelfe a blind power, ſeeing no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then by her underſtanding; how then, can ſhe incline too or proſecute any evill; when as the underſtanding propoſes no evill, nor can propoſe evill unto her? For in God whom the underſtanding ſo clearely and intuitively propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to the will; what evill or ſhadow of evill can be found? or what want of good can be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended?
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2562:37"/> And here I cannot but admire,<note place="margin">Orig: I. peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch cap. 7. &amp; hom: 33. et 35. in Lucam.</note> how <hi>Origen</hi> (that flower of witts amongſt the Ancients) could find (unleſſe his writings be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted) that the beatified Soules, and <hi>Spirits</hi> might ſinne and tranſgreſſe: which his <hi>errour</hi> we may obſerve too too clearely in his writings: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it we may thus argue moſt unanſwerably: If the bleſſed Soules and Spirits, may ſinne, then by ſinne they may looſe their happineſſe, which is ſo contrary to the eſſentiall condition thereof, that it were dotage ſo to imagine, that to be the true happineſſe of man, which is <hi>defectible, amiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,</hi> and may be loſt: moſt cleare it is, <hi>that that cannot be true happineſſe, the aeternity</hi> whereof may <hi>be doubted</hi> of: Or elſe we muſt admitt, that the beatified together with the complacence of ſinne, may continue happy: the which is impoſſible, and implies contradiction. For if perfect happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, do neceſſarily, yea eſſentially exclude <hi>all evill,</hi> how then can it admitt that <hi>evill,</hi> which<note place="margin">Pro. 14. 34. Mat. 25. 48.</note> is the <hi>evill of all evills, the evill that made mankind miſerable,</hi> the evill that <hi>onely makes nations miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:</hi> the evill for the puniſhing of which, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill of hell fire was onely provided: and for ever againſt the reprobates foreknowne and deſigned. How then, (I ſay) can the laſt happineſſe of man admitt this evill, which is ſo contrary to that moſt happy and holy ſtate, that nothing, <hi>which is polluted with him, can ever or ſhall ever enter</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reve. 21. 27. Auguſt. in pſal. 119.</note> 
                  <hi>thereinto.</hi> But ſo it is not above at the <hi>Lambes</hi> table; there the pure, truely pure, and onely pure, have admittance. <hi>Austen</hi> aptly. <hi>Bleſſed
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2562:38"/> are the pure and unſpotted in the way,</hi> as if the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſhould have ſaid,</hi> I know <hi>what thou wouldeſt, thou deſireſt</hi> happineſſe; <hi>if then thou willt be happy,</hi> be thou <hi>pure, be thou unſpotted:</hi> So then cleare it is that the beatified cannot ſinne: for beatified they cannot be, unleſſe they be firſt purified from all ſinne, how then being beatified may they committ ſinne? The truth of this point, of the <hi>impeccability</hi> of the beatified <hi>Soules</hi> and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, I declare thus. The <hi>beatified</hi> and happy by<note place="margin">How the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified be come impeceable.</note> the cleare viſion of God, are ſo determined and inclined, with a glorious neceſſity to <hi>love</hi> him, that as they cannot but love him as their laſt end, and cheefeſt good: ſo they cannot but referre all other actions and affections whatſoever elſe they may there have, to the glory of him, as to their laſt end: how then is it poſſible, that they ſhould tranſgreſſe or ſwarve from God, and ſo ſinne? Surely they cannot; and this <hi>impecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> they have, not by any extraordinary grace graunted unto them, For that purpoſe; for their very eſtate, and condition of ſeeing God, with ſo cleare a <hi>viſion;</hi> of loving him, with ſo unmoove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a <hi>love,</hi> of delighting in him, with ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable a <hi>joy,</hi> requires that they ſhould not have any left a poſſibility to ſwarve from him, And in truth, to ſtand within the principles of the light of nature, the Rules of <hi>divinity</hi> and <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy;</hi> it is more poſſible and probable: that a heavy <hi>milſtone,</hi> ſhould naturally moove and aſcend upwards from the <hi>Center</hi> of the earth (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which or neere unto which it hath a naturall
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2562:38"/> inclination by the whole force of his nature) then that the beatified Soules and Spirits, ſhould ſwarve and ceaſe from their <hi>love</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>delight</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> whom they ſo clearely, and preſentially, ſee and behold as their laſt end, the marke of their deſires, the totall object of their happineſſe, their onely and cheefeſt good. And ſo we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, how idle that reaſon is, wherewith ſome endeavour to proove, that the beatified Soules and Spirits are <hi>peccable:</hi> becauſe forſooth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of their wills (which intrinſecally requires that they ſhould be free, and at liberty) is not chaunged nor altered: True: the liberty of their wills is not perverted nor deſtroyed: but they<note place="margin">The will of men beatified hath no liberty about her laſt end.</note> are ſo perfected in the higheſt degree of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, unto which they can poſſibly attaine. And here I cannot paſſe to note, as a point of ignorance, for any one to thinke that the will hath, or can have a liberty of freedome to love,<note place="margin">See Aquinas. 1. q. 81. et 1. 2.</note> or not to love: to embrace or not to embrace, her laſt end, her cheefeſt and onely good, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of her happineſſe: ſo clearely and preſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally propoſed unto her, and as ſuch embraced by her.</p>
               <p>The jeſter in the play could tell, what end man deſired, yea what end man neceſſarily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, yea could not but deſire: to weet, <hi>to be happy:</hi> and yet theſe can finde, or preſume to finde, how the beatified Soules and Spirits, can in their very ſtate of happineſſe, have a liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or indiſſerency to love or not to love, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, or not to embrace the infinite Godneſſe of God, and their
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2562:39"/> laſt happineſſe: which with ſuch unſpeakeable joy, peace, and reſt, they hould and poſſeſſe in their bedds of that celeſtiall paradiſe: And of<note place="margin">Auguſt in pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</note> the purity and neceſſity whereof, <hi>Auſten</hi> moſt divinely thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What ſhall be the delights</hi> of <hi>Saints?</hi> they ſhall be delighted <hi>in a multitude</hi> of <hi>peace: Let the</hi> wicked <hi>here rejoyce in multitude of gold, store of ſilver, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of ſervants, exceſſe of riotous and luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous feaſts: but thou, O thou Lover of God, what ſhall thy delights be? Thou ſhalt be delighted in multitude of peace, and reſt: thy gold peace, thy ſilver peace, thy poſſeſsion peace: Thy life peace, thy God peace, yea whatſoever thou canst deſire ſhall be to thy peace and peace to thee: here that which is gold to thee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſilver: that which is wine, cannot be bread, that which is light, cannot be to thee as food and drinke; but there thy God ſhall bee to thee all in all: thou ſhalt eate him that thou hunger not, thou ſhalt drinke him least thou thirst, thou ſhalt be lightened of him that thou be not blinde: thou ſhalt be held up by him, that thou fall not from him: he whole and entire ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe thee, wholy and intirely; want there with him thou ſhalt not ſuffer any, with whom thou ſhalt poſſeſſe all. Thou ſhalt have all of him, and hee all of thee, becauſe hee and thou, ſhalt be but one: which one, and all, he ſhall have, who ſhall poſſeſſe and hold his Saints in reſt and peace.</hi> Thus that Father moſt aptly and ſweetely, ſhewing God to be ſo poſſeſſed of the beatified, and the <hi>beatified</hi> ſo to poſſeſſe God, that they cannot deſire ought elſe, no not have ſo much as a <hi>velleity</hi> or weake <hi>deſire to delight,</hi> or reſt in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2562:39"/> ought elſe then in God; <hi>the God of their hearts</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 73.</note> 
                  <hi>deſire, and their portion for ever.</hi> Where then is that idle conceipt of thoſe, who affirme, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the bleſſed cannot ſee any thing in God, that may moove them, or incline them to ſinne, yet in reſpect of other I cannot tell what particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler actions (wherein God may imploy them) they may have ſome either <hi>inconſideration</hi> or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and ſo conſequently may in the doing of the ſame, ſinne and <hi>tranſgreſſe:</hi> and ſo to them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them being happy, that of the Poet may be applyed, <hi>It is the part of a foole</hi> to ſay <hi>I had not thought of it; I did not conſider</hi> it arightly. <hi>O the preſumption of witts,</hi> to thinke that thoſe bleſſed Spirits can have any ſuch ignorance or inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, as not to do the will of God clearely propoſed unto them: how ſhall not they know the will of him, whoſe <hi>face they ſo clearely ſee and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>behold?</hi> how ſhould <hi>not they doe his will who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in nothing more then in the performance of his will?</hi> The Church by Chriſts owne commaund prayes thus to God; <hi>Thy will be done in earth, as</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>it is in heaven.</hi> Whereby ſhee profeſſes, that in the heavens above, there is moſt perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence yeelded by the beatified <hi>unto God;</hi> becauſe nothing can be there done or admitted againſt his will, either out of intended wilfullneſſe, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended negligence.<note place="margin">Mat. 18. 10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe bleſſed Spirits <hi>that ever behold the face of God,</hi> that is in <hi>heaven,</hi> cannot have the leaſt veleity<note place="margin">Baruch. 3. 39.</note> orinclination, not to doe the will of their God, which is in <hi>heaven;</hi> Thoſe <hi>glorious ſtarres no ſooner
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2562:40"/> heare the call of their God, but they</hi> anſwere, we are ready: doth not <hi>David</hi> give unto them, as a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar of their honnour and happineſſe, <hi>that they</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 103. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>ever doe the will of the Lord? Prayſe the Lord, all yee his hoſts; yee his ſervants, that doe his pleaſure, prayſe the Lord.</hi> And ſo I conclude this point; affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that the beatified Soules and ſpirits, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peccable, being by contemplation made <hi>immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> and by an <hi>euerlaſting</hi> love made <hi>undefec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have ſufficiently ſhewed, that there cannot be a deficiency in the laſt happineſſe, by reaſon of the commitment of any ſine by the beatified; but what? can there be any deficiency, or <hi>defectibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> thereof, upon any other head or reſpect? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no, for then unworthily ſhould it be reputed the laſt end of thoſe Spirits, which <hi>ſhall have no end,</hi> and of thoſe ſoules, which being immortall, ſhall never dye nor <hi>ceaſe to bee.</hi> True happineſſe that cannot be, of the aeternity and endleſſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance whereof, doubt may be made. <hi>Auſten</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auſten de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitat. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</note> moſt excellently: <hi>What other is our end,</hi> then to <hi>come to that kingdome whereof there is no end?</hi> Divers do here queſtion, whether the laſt happineſſe in part, to weet, of the glorious love of God, and joyous delight in God, may ceaſe and fade; notwithſtanding the cleare viſion and ſight of God, do ſtill continue: where in to reſolve, is ſmal or no difficulty at al: for if the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God out of his abſolut power can ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as he is in himſelfe (infinitely good &amp;c.) to any of the beatified, &amp; yet they not love him, nor
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2562:40"/> actualy delight in him; I anſwere, that it is morally impoſſible, except in ſuch a caſe onely, that God would not concurre with ſuch his beatified, to the act of love and affection of delight; and then moſt cleare it is that in ſuch a caſe, (though they follow naturally one upon another) yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are really diſtinguiſhed; that one may be effected and not the other, God concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, with the power intellective, for the action of viſion; but not with the power of the will, for the act of love, and affection of delight. But what a vanity of witts, to ſeeke a knot where none is? Cleare it is, that the ſtate of the laſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of man ſhal be ſo perfect and conſummate, that well may there be ſome new addition of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticious and accidentall <hi>glory;</hi> but to thinke that there ſhould be any fading in that happineſſe in which as <hi>Bernard</hi> divinely, the <hi>Beatified are ever greene and growing in aeternity;</hi> were an injurious vanity, and blaſphemous <hi>dotage,</hi> againſt the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and honour of the Citty of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SIXTH SECTION:</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Conteines certaine obſervations, touching the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied bodyes of the beatified and their glorious qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHat hath beene ſaid touching the glory of the ſoules of the beatified, comes very ſhort of that which in truth it is; For if an <hi>admiring ſoule cannot:</hi> how ſhall a <hi>ſpeaking tongue,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:2562:41"/> be able <hi>to expreſſe the excellent eminencyes of the ſame?</hi> But it being ſo, that the beatified Soules want part of their <hi>conſummation</hi> untill their bodies ſhall be joyntly glorified with them: This place requires that wee ſhould adde ſomewhat, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Firſt obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> the glorious conditions, and ſtates of their glorified bodies. For which purpoſe, I obſerve firſt, that though at the diſſolution of man by death, the Soule being ſeparated, from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; ſhee (if holy and regenerated) be elevated to bliſſe and glory, her body on earth rotting and falling away into duſt and corruption; yet there remaineth in the Soule a naturall and moſt intime inclination, to have her body (by information and naturall conjunction) reunited to her againe; which inclination St. <hi>Auſten</hi> conceived to be<note place="margin">Auguſt lib. 12 in Gen. cap. 35.</note> ſo great, that he thought by the meanes thereof, the ſoules beatified to be ſo letted and hindred; that they cannot ſee and behold God before the reſurrection, ſo perfectly as they ſhall do after the ſame; In which his opinion though (with reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be it written) he was miſtaken, (for the cleare viſion and fruition of God depends no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the body, or <hi>animall</hi> affections thereof) yet hereby it is evident, that the Soule hath not her full and compleat happineſſe untill her <hi>yoke-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> after whom ſhee ſo naturally longeth, be to her un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted againe: I ſay <hi>longeth,</hi> for the deſire after the body is not <hi>immoderate,</hi> nor <hi>anxious:</hi> for ſhee knoweth, that at the time and houre ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, her body ſhall be reformed in <hi>the likeneſſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>of Christs glorified body,</hi> and be renuited to her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2562:41"/> which time, becauſe God hath ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it, ſhe dutifully and obediently tarrieth and expecteth, knowing aſſuredly, that though it bee long, yet that at length, coming it will come.</p>
               <p>Secondly I obſerve, that this inclination of the Soule, ariſes from this, that the Soules of men are not (as the Spirits of <hi>Angells</hi> are) compleate and perfect <hi>Subſtances,</hi> ſubſiſting by themſelves;<note place="margin">The Soule and body are as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall parts for the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man.</note> but they are parts onely of humane nature; the Soule one part, the body another; both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring to make a perfect ſubſiſting nature of man; the Soule and body of both of them, parts ſeparable; yet herein differing, that the Soule whether ſeparated or united, is naturallie immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall; the body whether ſeparated or united, by nature mortall: and yet herein agreeing, that as being naturall parts, (if united) they make one compleat whole ſubſtance; ſo if ſeparated) they have an inclination, moſt intime and natural (for the making up of the whole) to be reunited agayne. But to declare this point more clearely. The <hi>inclination</hi> of any thing, that is but a part of a whole, to be united to that part, wherewith it maketh the whole, is ſo naturall, that the ſame inclination cannot be removed, unleſſe the thing it ſelfe, which is the part, bee firſt <hi>destroyed;</hi> for example, the parts of a greene tree, being but halfe cleft and pulled aſunder, doe not with a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall force more endevour to reunite them ſelves together; then the naturall, and eſſentiall parts of any compleat <hi>ſubstance,</hi> (upon any ſeparation)
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2562:42"/> doe incline to bee reunited together agayne: the reaſon of which inclination I take to be this, <hi>that everye thing hath a naturall propenſion,</hi> for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of it ſelfe and his owne <hi>being.</hi> Now cleare it is, that the <hi>eſſe</hi> and <hi>being</hi> of a part, <hi>as a part,</hi> is for the making of the whole; ſo then a part, hath never a more perfect being, then when it is in the whole; for whoſe being, making, &amp; conſtitution naturally it is. What marvaile then, that every part naturall and eſſentiall (if ſeparated from the whole) have an inclination (for the making up of the whole) to be reunited to her fellowe part agayne? and ſo no merveyle it is, that the Soule being an <hi>Eſſentiall</hi> and <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> part, together with the <hi>body,</hi> for the making up of the <hi>ſubstance</hi> of man, if (ſhe being ſeparated from the body) have a naturall inclination, to bee reunited to the body agayne; that by the meanes of ſuch a union, man, who by death was diſſolved, and become no man, may by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſcitation of the body, and the reunition of the body to the Soule, bee made <hi>man agayne.</hi> Though this point be moſt cleare, both in <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> yet is it not conceipted by thoſe, who make the Soule only to bee the whole man; and the body to be no other, then the Soules <hi>waggon</hi> or <hi>chariot;</hi> ſo that the Soule is no otherwiſe in the body, then as the mariner is in the <hi>ſhipp,</hi> or the <hi>inhabitant</hi> in his dwelling houſe: Of this opinion <hi>Porphirie</hi> ſeemed to bee, who (as <hi>Austen</hi> writes<note place="margin">Auſten 12. de Civit.</note> of him) affirmed, that <hi>the Soule</hi> (if ſhe would bee happie) was of <hi>neceſſity</hi> to bee <hi>ſeparated and freed
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2562:42"/> from the body: And likewiſe</hi> of this opinion al thoſe <hi>Heritickes</hi> of neceſſity muſt bee, who make and teach a duality of <hi>God;</hi> a <hi>good</hi> one, and a <hi>bad</hi> one; the <hi>good</hi> God, author of Spirits and Soules; the bad God, author of the bodies and all ſuch habituall corruptions as are in them; needes I ſay muſt theeſe latter ſo teach, for if Soules bee not naturall formes of bodies, to quicken them, &amp; give life unto them; and with them as comparts, to make compleat compoſed ſubſtances, of the Perſons of men and women; then aſſuredly, no naturall inclination or propenſion, can bee in them, being ſeparated from the bodies, to bee reunited to them agayne; no more inclination certeynly, then there can be in him, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving once taſted of the tyrannie of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, can deſire to returne into it agayne.</p>
               <p>Thirdly I obſerve, the juſt diſpoſition of <hi>God,</hi> who hath ordeyned a generall reſuſcitation of bodies at the laſt day; that man accordingly as <hi>hee may have done eyther good or evill,</hi> may receave eyther a glorious reward, or an ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſe puniſhment in the bodye. Cleare it is, that not only the Soule, or only the body, but men and women compoſed both of body and ſoules, are thoſe who worke and doe; (for acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and deedes are of the Perſons themſelves) are thoſe (I ſay) who doe eyther good or evill, and conſequently, whole man and woman perfect and compleat Perſons, muſt appeare to <hi>receave according as they have done in their bodie eyther good or evill: Wee muſt all appeare before the judgement
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2562:43"/> ſeate of Chriſt</hi> (ſayth the <hi>Apoſtle) that every one may</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>ceceave, according as hee maye have done in his body, eyther good or evill.</hi> Not onely bodies then, nor Soules alone; but men and women, Perſons compleate and conſummate, muſt appeare; I ſay conſummate, for ſuch is the Phraſe of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> where ſpeaking of<note place="margin">Heb. 11. 13.</note> the Fathers and Ancients of the old teſtament, who by the teſtimonie of Fayth were approved, ſayth thus, They <hi>receaved not the repromiſsion and promiſe, God providing better for us, that without us they ſhould not be conſummated;</hi> ſo hee ſpeaketh. And this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſummation (which is when the bodie being rayſed up and ſhall be joyned to the Soule agayne) is that whereof holy <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh thus,<note place="margin">Iob. 14. 15.</note> making it the verie worke of the right hand of <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, <hi>Thou ſhalt</hi> reach out thy <hi>right hand, to the worke of thy handes;</hi> or as the <hi>Chaldaicke pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſe</hi> hath it, <hi>Thou ſhalt be gracious to the worke of thy hands.</hi> How this; but by a powerfull and gracious reſuſcitation, and rayſing up of her body from her bed of duſt and corruption, and reuniting the ſame agayne, unto the Soule, whereby, (it being reunited) becomes quickened,<note place="margin">Iob. 9. 25. &amp; 26.</note> with the Spirit of life? The hope of this, was ſo deare and preciouſe to holy and moſt venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Iob;</hi> that on the <hi>dunghill</hi> of his miſeries, with a triumphant kind of joy, hee layed up in his boſome the joy full expectation hereof: <hi>I know,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>that my redeemer liveth, and that at the laſt day, I ſhall be compaſſed about with my skinne, and that in my fleſh, I ſhall ſee</hi> God my <hi>Saviour; and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2562:43"/> that myne owne eyes ſhall behould him, and not any other for mee.</hi> And in this expectation, hee dayly dwelt, according as he profeſſes in another place: <hi>All the dayes of this my</hi> warfarre, <hi>I expect and looke, untill my chaunge, and immutation be come.</hi> Which<note place="margin">Iob. 14. 14.</note> chaunge and immutation, is that verie thing, which now wee have in conſideration; to weet, the glorious ſtate, and condition of the bodies of thoſe, who in this their pilgrimage, may have walked in true fayth towards their <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not doubted of amongſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but that the ſame individuall Perſon is to appeare, &amp; is or ſhall bee glorified both in body and ſoule; who in this mortall life, hath kept his fayth; <hi>faythfullie</hi> and obediently ſeruing <hi>God;</hi> not taking, or receaving <hi>his Soule</hi> in vayne; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Pſal. 24. 4.</note> as the Soule is the ſame <hi>individuallye</hi> (for it never periſhed) ſo likewiſe the verie body, muſt bee the ſame <hi>individuallye,</hi> yea, and the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall union and conjunction whereby the Soule and body are joyned together, muſt be the ſame <hi>individuallye,</hi> and in unity of <hi>number;</hi> which though reaſon conceaves not, yet <hi>fayth</hi> aſſecures and warrantes; And ſo conſequently cleare it is, that the immutation and chaunge, whereof the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> and holy <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeake, is not becauſe there is another Soule, or another body, or another union of body and Soule (for all theſe three are the ſame individuallye and numerically) but the whole chaunge and immutation is, in reſpect of ſome glorious <hi>properties</hi> and <hi>qualities</hi> which the bodies reſuſcitated to glorie ſhall have, which
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2562:44"/> they never had whilſt they were yet mortall; fro as the <hi>Soules</hi> and <hi>Spirits</hi> have their ſpeciall glories, ſo likewiſe ſhall the bodies have theirs. Theſe<note place="margin">Foure glorious qualities of the glorified bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</note> qualities and properties, are commonly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed to bee fowre; to weet, <hi>Impaſſibilitie, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillity, Agility, Clarity: Impaſsibilitie</hi> whereby the body is made uncapable of any contrary paſſion, or violent impreſſion: <hi>Subtillity,</hi> whereby the body is made not a Spirit, but like unto a <hi>Spirit,</hi> to bee able to penetrate, or paſſe where it could not before: <hi>Agility,</hi> whereby it is indewed with ſuch a velocity and Swifenes, that the <hi>beatified</hi> may followe the <hi>Lambe</hi> whitherſoever <hi>he goeth: Clarity,</hi> whereby al deformitie, or naturall <hi>obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> being taken away, <hi>the body</hi> becomes <hi>bright,</hi> ſhining and reſplendent; but wee muſt explicate theſe things more particularlye, and yet with all brevitie poſſible. I beginne with the firſt.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Impaſsibilitye.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Impaſsibilitye</hi> muſt needes be graunted, as a partiall dowrie to glorified bodies; for if they ſhould be paſſible as before, then conſequently they ſhould bee corruptible, which as it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the nature of felicity, that eſſentially in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes a participated <hi>aternity,</hi> ſo is it expreſſely, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> doctrine, where he profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>that our bodies which are ſowne in corruption, ſhall riſe up in incorruption.</hi> But though it be moſt appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that glorified bodies ſhall bee impaſſible; yet is it not ſo eaſily to explicate and open, from
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2562:44"/> whence this impaſſibility doth immediately a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe; or what is, the immediate cauſe thereof: The <hi>Apostle</hi> tells us, that <hi>what is ſowed in weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and infirmity, riſeth up in power and vertue; which vertus or power,</hi> I take to be the immediate cauſe of <hi>impaſsibility;</hi> or elſe to be <hi>impaſsibility</hi> it ſelfe. But what is this <hi>vertue</hi> and power? Is it<note place="margin">1.</note> a ſupernaturall vertue, making the elementary parts and qualities, to be of another nature, then now they are? Not ſo; for nature muſt not be chaunged or deſtroyed, but perfected. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">2.</note> ſhall theſe elementary qualities, by Gods hand be limited and ſtayed, in their actions and operations, that they ſhall not worke one againſt another, for their mutuall deſtruction? Not ſo; for then, this impaſſibility ſhould not be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall vertue, as a dowry immanent in the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified body; (which is againſt the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention) but onely an outward aſſiſtance of God. Againe, theſe elementary parts and qualities,<note place="margin">Impaſſibility is internall.</note> muſt have their ſeverall mixtions; for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of diverſe and diſtinct parts corporall, which cannot be, without a refraction and compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the elementary qualities themſelves one with another. Or <hi>Thirdly,</hi> may we thinke, that<note place="margin">3.</note> this vertue is a coeleſtiall kinde of <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> or ſubſtanciall quality, which united with the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary qualities and ſubſtances, doth temper and make thereby the bodies which are to be glorified, fit receptacles for their glorious ſoules? This though it ſeeme very probable, yet I will rather reſolve with <hi>Aquinas,</hi> that this vertue and<note place="margin">Supplem: q. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2. art 1.</note>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:2562:45"/> power of <hi>Impaſſibility</hi> flowes immediately from the ſoule herſelfe, which informing the body doth ſo perfectly and fully, ſubdue all the powers and qualities of the ſame, unto herſelfe; that no contrary agent, can be able to make any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent impreſſion, or action, upon, or againſt the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, for the corruption &amp; deſtruction of the ſame: or may be able to draw it from that quiet and peaceable ſtate, wherein it reſts. <hi>Auſten</hi> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently: <hi>God hath made</hi> the Soule <hi>of ſo powerfull a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Auguſt epiſt. 66. ad Dioſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> 
                     <hi>that from her glorious happineſſe there redounds to the body the vigour of incorruption.</hi> Cleare it is, that no agent can worke, with any violent or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary impreſſion, upon, or againſt any other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, or ſubject, to hurt or alter the ſame, unleſſe the ſame Agent, be more powerfull then the other is; on which, or againſt which, it worketh: which being clearely true; likewiſe cleare it is; that no corporall creature, which hath in it <hi>contrary</hi> ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary <hi>quallities,</hi> can be of greater power and force, then a glorified body is, to worke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt or upon the ſame. So long therefore, as the <hi>glorified</hi> Soule ſhall be ſubject to God, and the glorified body, be ſubject to the Soule; ſo long it ſhall be impoſſible, for any corporall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent whatſoever, to have a tranſeunt action or impreſſion, which may any way <hi>alter</hi> or hurt the ſame. And this is that immutation and <hi>change</hi> whereof the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> not onely ſpeakes but glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 51.</note> 
                     <hi>We ſhall not all ſleepe, but wee ſhall all be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</hi> Where he makes this immutation, to be a chaunge, from <hi>paſſibility</hi> to <hi>impaſſibility;</hi> and to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2562:45"/> be peculiar onely to the elect, whereof the <hi>repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,</hi> ſhall have no part, nor portion at all.</p>
                  <p>And yet, though we graunt an <hi>impaſsibility</hi> to the bodies <hi>glorified,</hi> ſo that they ſhall not be ſubject to any violent, or contrary impreſſions;<note place="margin">The Beatified ſhall have all ſuch ſenſitive actions which include not Corruption.</note> yet we may not deny, but that there ſhall be all ſuch ſenſitive actions, (and conſequently anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable paſſions which include not <hi>corruption</hi>) of <hi>ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hearing, feeling, ſmelling, taſting</hi> and ſuch like, as may be fitting for that place. Of <hi>ſight</hi> cleare<note place="margin">Iob. 19. 26.</note> it is; for <hi>Iob</hi> profeſſes <hi>that his eyes ſhall behold God his Saviour;</hi> and moſt frequent are other teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Scripture for the ſame. <hi>Hearing</hi> cannot be denyed, for as the Saints ſhall <hi>inceſſantly</hi> with vocall <hi>praiſe,</hi> (the Pſalmiſt profeſſing that the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultations</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 149. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>of God, ſhall be in their throates</hi>) magnifie God; ſo no doubt may be made, but that their vocall <hi>Allelu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>as</hi> ſhall be mutually heard and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; yea who can doubt, but that the beatifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhall ſpeake to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> to them? <hi>Goe too; Good and faithfull Servants,</hi> ſaith Chriſt; <hi>all haile Glorious</hi> God and <hi>Lord,</hi> ſing <hi>they; Benediction, thankſgiving,</hi> is their glorious note for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. <hi>Feeling</hi> we may not deny, for that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes not any corruption, and if agreeing to ſenſe, it is a perfection not a defect of nature. And that <hi>glorified</hi> bodies be <hi>palpable</hi> and may be <hi>felt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc. 24. 39.</note> that of <hi>Chriſt</hi> makes it moſt cleare, <hi>Feele, and ſee, for a ſpirit hath not fleſh and bones, as you ſee mee to have.</hi> Neither of the ſenſe of ſmelling, may any queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be made; becauſe, for the ſenſation thereof, there is no corruptible or corporall immutation neceſſarily required.</p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:2562:46"/>
                  <p>Touching the ſenſe of <hi>taste;</hi> ſome difficulty may be made; and yet though there be no deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>taſte</hi> by eating or drinking delicious meates or dainties (ſuch as the voluptuous of theſe times make their <hi>God</hi>) notwithſtanding it is not abſurd to thinke, that the glorified bodyes by <hi>Gods</hi> ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, ſhall have, ſome delicious and pleaſant moyſture, reſting upon the place of taſt, that ſo by ſuch a meanes, that ſenſible part may have her full reſt and content. The beſt reaſons, for this which I have ſaid, touching the perfection of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſenſes, I take to be theſe few, <hi>first,</hi> that as the body ſhall have her perfection and reward, becauſe ſhee was ſo familiar, and individuall a companion of the Soule, in the ſuffering for<note place="margin">Reaſons why there ſhall be glorious acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Senſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</note> 
                     <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or her ſubjection to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> So likewiſe, the ſenſitive <hi>parts,</hi> and faculties, which have been <hi>inſtruments</hi> of the <hi>Soule,</hi> in the exerciſe of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, ſhall alſo have their appointed <hi>reward. Againe,</hi> there can be no ſufficient reaſon, brought<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 13. 1 Cor. 6. 19. Luk. 10. 27. 2 Cor. 5. 10.</note> againſt what I have ſaid; why it ſhould not be ſo. Againe; he that will ſeriouſly peruſe the 5. and 25. chapters of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Matthewes Goſpell,</hi> and the 22. of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Luke;</hi> where <hi>Chriſt</hi> promiſes, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes<note place="margin">Mat. 5. and 25. Luk: 22.</note> his glorious rewards, to his faithfull fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers; and where <hi>Lazarus</hi> is deſcribed, to have taſted his very felicity (a thing which the rich glutton importunely deſired) will not eaſily be induced to thinke this which I have here ſet downe to be untrue or falſe. And ſo I conclude this point with this obſervation, that if (as I have ſhewed above) there be in the Soule glorified an
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2562:46"/> 
                     <hi>impeccability</hi> and <hi>indefectibility,</hi> ſo that they cannot ſin; &amp; in the body, an impaſſibility, not to receive any the leaſt impreſſion of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariety and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that may be: how firme then? how ſtable then? yea how everlaſting then? is that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>state: which hath this participated aeternity aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally</hi> that it cannot periſh nor decay? Who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly conſiders this, and longs not, to have a ſpeedy diſſolution of this terreſtriall houſe? of this <hi>cotage</hi> of dirt and clay? that ſo he may be<note place="margin">Iob. 4. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>preſent with the Lord; and</hi> have a <hi>houſe aeternall and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>everlaſting? not made with hands, but ſuch a one, as the ſpirit of the Lord ſhall frame and eſtabliſh? O how amiable are thy dwellings, thou Lord of hoſts? my Soule</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 84. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>longeth and my heart fainteth after the Courts of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Subtilitie.</head>
                  <p>THis dowrie gift, which is generallie called Subtilitie, I would rather ſpeaking with the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> call <hi>Spiritualty;</hi> for in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> hee affirmeth thus, <hi>It is ſowed a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall body, but it riſeth a ſpirituall body;</hi> and againe,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 44, 47. 48. 49.</note> 
                     <hi>The firſt man is of the earth, earthly; The ſecond man, is the Lord from heaven; As is the earthy, ſuch are they that are earthy; and as is the heavenly, ſuch alſo are they, that are heavenly:</hi> And as wee have borne <hi>the Image of the earthy, wee ſhall alſo beare the Image of the heavenly.</hi> Thus the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle;</hi> whereout many excellent obſervations might bee made. But I call it <hi>Spiritualty</hi> not as
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2562:47"/> though (which ſome falſly have affirmed) the body were chaunged into the Soule and <hi>Spirit,</hi> for ſo that which is rayſed ſhould not bee <hi>man,</hi> conſiſting of Soule and <hi>Body;</hi> but a third diſtinct thing, different from Man; and conſequently the myſtery of the reſurrection of the fleſh ſhould bee quite taken away; for <hi>Reſurrection</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires that the ſame thing which fell, bee rayſed up againe. Neyther doe I call it <hi>Spiritualty</hi> as though the body after reſurrection were made thin, and rare, like the wynd and ayre, as the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tychians</hi> of ould did affirme; denying the bodyes glorified to bee <hi>palpable:</hi> but I call it <hi>Spiritualty</hi> by reaſon of a more <hi>powerfull influence,</hi> and that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion which the <hi>Soule</hi> ſhall have into and over the <hi>Body</hi> after the <hi>reſurrection,</hi> then it ever had or could have in the time of her mortalitye. This though it bee hard to explicate, yet ſure I am that in ſo affirming &amp; calling of it <hi>Spiritualty</hi> I ſpeake in the phraſe of the <hi>Apoſtle;</hi> but as for <hi>Subtility</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 44.</note> which in true and proper ſignification ſignifyes a property whereby ſuch things as are ſpirituall have a <hi>penetrative</hi> and <hi>piercing</hi> vertue to paſſe and<note place="margin">Ariſto. lib. 2. de Generat. tex. 50</note> pierce into and <hi>through,</hi> the corpulent parts of any thing that hath a bodye and is corpulent, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving dmenſions and parts; I cannot ſee how it can bee given to the glorified bodyes, which after <hi>reſurrection</hi> have the ſame <hi>extenſive</hi> and corpulent <hi>parts</hi> for <hi>quantity</hi> and fulnes of matter or bodili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; as they had before the reſurrection: and can no more penetrate, pierce or enter into or thorough any true bodily and corporall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2562:47"/> which hath the dimenſions of quantity, to weet, <hi>thicknes, breadth, length,</hi> then they could<note place="margin">Auguſt. tract 121 in Ioh. Chryſoſt. hom. 89. in Ioh. Ambroſ. in 24. luc. Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ar. ub. 3 definit. Hiero-Epiſt. ad Pammach. Ioh 20, 26.</note> before their reſurrection, in the time of their <hi>mortality</hi> and corruption. And although it may bee probably affirmed with diverſe Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that the body of our <hi>ſaviour (who entered into his diſciples the dores beeing ſhut)</hi> did by powerfull penetration paſſe thorough the doore, yet wee maye not attribute the ſame as a thing naturall to his glorified body, it having the ſame <hi>dimenſions</hi> of <hi>quantity</hi> for bodilines and fulnes of matter which it had before; but wee muſt with Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity attribute the ſame to the power of his <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc. 137. Auguſt. Epſ. 3. ad Voluſianum Heb. 4. 18. Iob. 37. 18</note> 
                     <hi>to whom no word is impoſſible;</hi> for he that could enter into the wombe <hi>the ſecret of the moſt pure ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin not violated, as Auguſtine and Nazianzene</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently; Hee who could <hi>penetrate the heavens</hi> which are more ſolid and ſtrong then braſſe, and yet receaue no bruiſe in his body, nor make any rent in them; wee may not doubt but that by the <hi>omnipotenty</hi> of his power <hi>hee could enter in into his diſciples the dores being ſhut.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to conculde this point wherein the holy Scriptures bee ſo ſparing; though with the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> wee give <hi>Spiritualty</hi> to the glorified bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, whereby it may ſeeme that in truth they are become Spirituall (which is true in the ſenſe I have expreſſed) yet are they not ſo Spirituall but that they are palpaple and may bee touched<note place="margin">Luc. 24. 39.</note> and felt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Feele &amp; ſee,</hi> ſayth Chriſt, <hi>to his Apoſtles, for a Spirit hath not fleſh and bones as you ſee mee to have.</hi> Where I note that a body which is truly ſpiritual,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2562:48"/> may withall bee really palpaple and bee touched and felt alſo, though it bee againſt that knowen<note place="margin">Gregor. hom. 26 in Euangel.</note> ſaying of <hi>Gregory</hi> called the great, a Pope of <hi>Rome. Of neceſſity all what ſo ever may bee felt or handled is ſubject to Corruption.</hi> But perhaps hee meant, that ſo it was ordinarily according to the courſe of naturall things, as they are in this ſtate of morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. The reader may here expect that I ſhould more amply open and explicate what this <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualty</hi> may bee; I confeſſe my Ignorance, I had rather heare a maſter then bee my ſelf a <hi>Teacher;</hi> only I reſolve that it is a ſpirituall influence into, and a powerfull Dominion of a <hi>Soule</hi> Glorious over a Glorified <hi>Body,</hi> whereby the <hi>Body</hi> may ſeeme as it were to bee freed and cleared from all ſuch corporall imperfections and defections as are incident to ſubſtances that are bodily, and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, I meane ſuch imperfections and defects as doe not eſſentially follow the nature of <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity</hi> and <hi>Bodilines</hi> it ſelf; that is, all ſuch defects and imperfectious as precede and goe before, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, or follow after <hi>Generation, Augmentation</hi> or ſuch like corporall motions, which ſerve for the increaſe or conſervation of humane nature. And ſurely moſt neceſſary it is that all ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and imperfectious ſhould ceaſe; for without the ceſſation of them it cannot bee well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, how the <hi>Beatified</hi> both in body and Soule ſhould bee elevated into <hi>that liberty of Glory which</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 21. Galat. 4.</note> is promiſed to the childeren of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Citiſens</hi> of that <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> above, which is both Glorious and freed from all ſervitude of corruption.</p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:2562:48"/>
                  <p>Cleare experience teacheth that to bee moſt true which the booke of Wiſedome complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly<note place="margin">Sap. 9. 15:</note> delivereth. <hi>That the Corruptible body over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loadeth and aggravateth the ſoule. And that</hi> the earthly habitation preſſeth downe the mynde <hi>meditating upon many things.</hi> Moſt neceſſary then it is, that in that ſtate of <hi>felicity</hi> and full liberty where the Soules <hi>Beatified</hi> inceſſantly ſee <hi>God</hi> and meditate upon <hi>God,</hi> that they ſhould bee freed from all groſſe and heavy clogs and hinderances, that ſo with all their forces and endeavours they may bend themſelves to the contemplation, loue and fruition of the infinit <hi>Goodnes</hi> of <hi>God</hi> ſo cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and preſentially propoſed unto them. And this is that which wee muſt call <hi>Spiritualty;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, if I may ſeeme to the Learned to be miſtaken, I deſire from them ſome better and more full de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of this dowry of <hi>Subtility.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Agility.</head>
                  <p>THis dowry gift of <hi>Agility</hi> is a glorious quality or vertue, whereby the bodyes of the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied are totally ſubject to the Soules, as to moſt powerfull Movers: to be moved by them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all reſiſtance or leaſt reluctancy that may be thought on: which <hi>Agility</hi> or <hi>Facility</hi> as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive they have, becauſe the ſoule hath a moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute dominion over them, and doth by a redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancy and emanation impart unto them a glorious quickning and vivacity or livelines, farre beyond that which any mortall creature in their bodily
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2562:49"/> heavy parts can have. And this either by the meanes of a greater perfection of glorified Soules, or by the meanes of more perfect inſtruments for motion, then thoſe which corruptible bodies u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually have. This <hi>Agility</hi> or <hi>Facility</hi> for <hi>motion,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it make the bodies glorified very tractable to the ſoules for motion, ſo that we may in a ſort ſay with <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Auſten. Whereto ſoever the will ſhal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Auguſt. lib: 22. de Civit. cap. altimo.</note> 
                     <hi>there preſently the body</hi> (as it were in a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) <hi>ſhall or may be:</hi> yet we may not graunt unto the ſaid bodies any <hi>inſtant tanean</hi> motion: ſo that in an imagined inſtant of time (I ſay imagined in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, for time hath no true or reall inſtant either as part or period and end of it ſelfe) they may make any true reall corporall motion or <hi>mooving.</hi> Howſoever diverſe Schoolemen may to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary have dreamed. For doth it not imply in termes, and involve <hi>contradiction,</hi> that that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is a ſucceſſiue paſſing over, or in ſpace from place to place (as all corporall motion and moving is) ſhould be, and not in ſome <hi>durance</hi> and continuance of <hi>time</hi> according to the greater or leſſe velocity and ſwiftneſſe thereof.</p>
                  <p>And yet notwithſtanding, the corporall moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of glorified bodies may be very ſodaine and in (as it were) imperceptible moments of <hi>time;</hi> like as the <hi>Sunne</hi> beames, the which as it were in a moment (becauſe in an unperceivable moment of time) doe fill this whole <hi>hemiſphere</hi> with their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious<note place="margin">Aug. epiſt. 44. Sap. 3. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Luſtre. Auſten</hi> affirmes it, and I dare not deny it: And ſo I interpret thoſe words of the booke of Wiſdome (if they are to be underſtood
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2562:49"/> of the glorified). <hi>The righteous ſhall ſhine, and as</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 20. and 21. Luk 24.</note> 
                     <hi>ſparks among the stubble, they ſhall runne too and fro:</hi> Whereby, I take it, their <hi>agility</hi> and <hi>facility</hi> for motion is figured. And if we arightly conſider what is recorded in ſacred Scriptures, touching the ſundry ſoudayne corporall apparitions and diſapearings of our Saviour after his reſurrection, and how that the bodyes of the beatified ſhall be made <hi>conformable</hi> to the <hi>Clarity</hi> (and ſo anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 20.</note> to other glorious qualities) of his glorified body, there will no juſt reaſon be ſhewed for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying ſuch a glorious <hi>agility,</hi> either to the body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or to the <hi>glorified</hi> bodyes of his Saints.</p>
                  <p>And although we give to the glorified bodyes of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Saints ſuch a glorious <hi>nimble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and <hi>Agility,</hi> yet if we obſerve the phraſes of ſacred Scriptures, we ſhall finde that the glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that glorious ſtate of happineſſe, are ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome recorded to have uſed ſuch extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>agility</hi> and <hi>nimbleneſſe</hi> of <hi>motion.</hi> We reade that <hi>they ſhall follow the Lambe</hi> whitherſoever he<note place="margin">Reve. 14. 4.</note> goeth, which following is interpreted even by the <hi>Lambe</hi> himſelfe to be a walking, which muſt be ſo decent and grave as becomes that glorious ſtate. For thus he profeſſeth hereof: <hi>They ſhall</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reve. 3. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>walke with me in whites, for they are worthy.</hi> Now this <hi>walking</hi> muſt be ſuch as beſeemes the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Majeſty</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the honour of his Saints <hi>Glorious, Grave, Divine, Magnificent;</hi> Aud ſurely it were no leſſe then folly once to dreame that the glorified ſhall have any games or ſports in cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and running up and downe. No, no, ſuch va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities which
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2562:50"/> earthly minds do over highly priſe, do not beſeeme their ſtates of <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>Majeſty;</hi> And yet though we deny them to have any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely runnings or dancings, we may not affirme them to be ſo penned up as though they had no glorious <hi>reſtings, perambulations</hi> and <hi>walkings;</hi> They have doubtleſſe their ſittings on <hi>ſeates</hi> of <hi>Iudgement;</hi> They have their <hi>religious</hi> and <hi>Reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall ſtandings</hi> up, <hi>bowing</hi> downe, <hi>proſtrations</hi> and<note place="margin">Ephe. 2. 5. Revelat. 3. 2. Luk. 22. 30. Mat. 19 28. Revelat. 4. 4. 10. and 7. 9.</note> the <hi>caſting downe of their Crownes before the state of Majestye.</hi> How then can we deny unto them ſeemely divine motions? And notwithſtanding whitherto ſoever their motions leade them, they have the glorious preſence of God with them; for God by the vertue and <hi>immenſity</hi> of his <hi>all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſence</hi> being in all his Creatures, the glorified<note place="margin">Mat. 18. 10.</note> wereſover they be, <hi>they alwayes ſee his face,</hi> not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly above in the heavens, but even in the loweſt bowells of the earth, if any occaſion of ſervice, ſhould require their preſence there.</p>
                  <p>And can wee otherwiſe dreame but that thoſe glorious <hi>Angells</hi> who did miniſter to <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the<note place="margin">Mat. 4. 12.</note> wilderneſſe, did there (for by definitive preſence the ſubſtances and natures were in the wildernes not in heaven) did there I ſay behold the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Majeſty</hi> of the Father? And ſurely that which <hi>Gregory</hi> affirmes of the <hi>Angells</hi> truely; <hi>That they</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Greg. hom. 34. in Ezekiel.</note> 
                     <hi>runne as it were within God and in God,</hi> whitherto <hi>ſoever they are ſent,</hi> may alſo be truely affirmed of the glorified Saints, wheretoſoever they roule, and whereſoever they abide; <hi>they abide in God and roulle in God.</hi> It was truely ſaid by the <hi>Poet,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:2562:50"/> confirmed by the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that in God we live, we moove, and have our being, as certainly<note place="margin">Act. 17. 28.</note> it may be ſaid of the beatified, that <hi>they live, moove are, and have their glorious being in him; live</hi> of him, by partaking of his glorious life; <hi>move</hi> before him, by moſt prompt and ready obedience, alwayes doing his will; are in him by a glorious inpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God in them, and they in God, being <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 23.</note> 
                     <hi>into his owne glory.</hi> Againe in him, with him, and before him; with him never to be ſeparated from him; <hi>in</hi> him, diving into and ſwimming in the infinite ocean of his <hi>joy; before</hi> him alwayes beholding and delighting to behold the <hi>glory</hi> of his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and the Majeſty of his <hi>glory.</hi> So likewiſe God in <hi>them</hi> with them and before them <hi>In them</hi> by the glorious bright and light of his countenance illuſtrating them within; <hi>with them</hi> ever ſupporting them with the left hand of his protection, and filling them with the joyes and pleaſures of his <hi>right hand</hi> of conſolation; <hi>before</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.</note> them for all <hi>aternityes</hi> by their glorious viſion and fruition of him; himſelfe to ſatiate them, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to ſade or cloy them; <hi>ever deſirous to ſee and delighting to ſee.</hi> O how amourouſly in longing deſire after theſe things cryed out that ſweet ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of <hi>Iſraell: Glorious</hi> things are ſpoken of thee <hi>O</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 87. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>City of God!</hi> O thou City of God, ſo glorious <hi>are the things</hi> which are <hi>in thee, that no tongue can with ſufficiency, ſpeake the least part of them:</hi> and no marvell, for what tongue can ſpeake them <hi>which</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 64. 4. 1 Cor. 2. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>eye hath not ſeene, eare hath not heard, neither the heart of man hath conceived, neither can conceive in this
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2562:51"/> ſtate of mortality, what God hath prepared for thoſe that love him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Clarity.</head>
                  <p>THat which the <hi>Apostle</hi> calls glory, ſpeaking<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 43.</note> thus, <hi>The body is ſowen in ignoblenes, it riſeth againe in glory,</hi> is generally by Divines termed and called <hi>Clarity,</hi> and this nothing at all from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſenſe; for in the place alleaged, he teaching that at the Generall reſurrection the <hi>Glories</hi> of the bodies glorified ſhalbe <hi>different</hi> and diverſe, one exceeding the other, hee uſeth this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 45.</note> for the ſame, <hi>Like as oneſtarre differeth from another in Clarity</hi> (the brightneſſe of the ſtarres being more properly, called Clarity then glory) <hi>ſo ſhall the reſurrection of the dead bee.</hi> Now what manner of <hi>Clarity</hi> this ſhall bee, it is not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to expeſſe; if wee call to mynd what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Clarity</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> that was wherwith the body of <hi>Christ</hi> was adorned at the time of his<note place="margin">Mat. 17. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Tranſfiguration, when his face did ſhyne as the ſun, and his rayment was white as the light. S. Mark, addes that his rayment became ſhyning, exceeding whyte as the ſnow, ſo as no fuller on the earth can whyten them.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mark. 9. 3.</note> But cleare it is, that our vile and humble bodyes at the daye of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> ſhall bee tranſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and by a glorious <hi>immutation</hi> bee made like to the reſplendant and bright ſhinning body of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> ſo ſayth <hi>Paule</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians;<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 20.</note> And Chriſt promiſeth in the Goſpell, <hi>That the Righteous ſhall ſhyne like the Sun in the kingdome
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2562:51"/> of their Father.</hi> Loe <hi>Christs face</hi> on earth did ſhine,<note place="margin">Mat. 13. 43.</note> and now in heaven doth ſhyne like the <hi>Sun;</hi> and to the Righteous it is promiſed, that though now they are as the <hi>very of ſcumme of the world, yet their faces ſhall ſhyne like the Sun in the kingdome of their Father.</hi> But here note that though it bee ſayd that <hi>Christs</hi> body &amp; the Saynts bodies ſhall ſhyne like one and the ſame thing; never the leſſe this muſt not bee taken in full equality of <hi>Clarity &amp; bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chryſoſt: in Mat.</note> 
                     <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> excellently: <hi>But if the face of the Lord did ſhyne as the Sun, and the Saynts ſhall ſhyne as the Sun;</hi> ſhall then <hi>the Lords Clarity and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants bee equall?</hi> Not ſo, <hi>but becauſe nothing is found to bee more bright then the Sun, therefore to give an example of the future reſurrection, both the face of our Lord is ſayed to ſhyne, and the righteous alſo are ſayd to ſhyne as the Sun;</hi> Whereby wee cannot but obſerve how exceeding bright and reſplendant the <hi>Clarity</hi> of our glorified bodies ſhall bee; for if they ſhall ſhyne as the <hi>Sun,</hi> and the <hi>Sun</hi> ſhall<note place="margin">Iſa. 30. 26. Chryſoſt, in Mat.</note> ſhyne at the day of Iudgement ſeventimes brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then now it doth; then may wee boldly with <hi>Chryſostome</hi> ſay, <hi>though there ſhall bee no chaunge in nature, yet there ſhall be the addition or putting to of an unenarrable Clarity and brightnes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which brightnes and <hi>Clarity</hi> we may not only conceave that it ſhall bee a tranſeunt Light upon the ſuperficies and out ſyde of the body, like as the <hi>Suns</hi> beames, without any immutation inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, doe ſpread themſelves upon a wall; No, no; there ſhall bee a true internall immutation by a glorious <hi>Clarity</hi> and brightnes, which ſhall make
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2562:52"/> the glorified bodies not only bright and cleare without, but alſo fulgent and ſhyning within, and thoroughout. So that the glory of the Soule may thorough the body is it were by a glaſſe, in ſuch a manner bee ſeene and beheld in ſuch ſort as a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall <hi>glory</hi> may bee beheld and ſeene; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in like ſort, as the <hi>Coulour</hi> of the body may be ſeene in a <hi>glaſſe,</hi> or rather as the life of the ſoule is ſeene and obſerved in and by the <hi>vivacity</hi> and <hi>Livelines</hi> which it imparts by action and motion to the outward viſible parts of the body.</p>
                  <p>And if I miſconceane not, in reſpect of this glorious <hi>tranſlucency</hi> and tranſparency, the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and <hi>Clarity</hi> of the celeſtiall <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> is in the Revelation of <hi>S. Iohn</hi> thus &amp; in like ſort deſcribed: <hi>And hee caryed mee away in the ſpirit into an high</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reve. 21. 10. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>and great mountayne, and ſhewed mee the great City holy Hieruſalem</hi> (which I interpret the Glorious ſtate of the Saints Triumphant) <hi>deſcending out of heaven, from God having the glory of God. And her light was like unto a ſtone moſt precious, even like a Iaſperſtone as cleare as Chryſtall.</hi> And agayne in<note place="margin">v. 18. 19. 20. &amp;c.</note> the 18. and other verſes following, <hi>And the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the wall of it was of Iaſper, and the City was pure gould like unto cleare glaſſe, and the foundations of the wall of the City were garniſhed with all manner of precious ſtones. The firſt foundation was Iaſper, the ſecond Saphire, the third a Chalcedonye, the fourth an Emerauld, the fifth a Sardonix, the ſixth a Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius, the ſeventh a Chryſolite, the eighth a Berill, the ninth a Topaz, the tenth a Chryſopraſſe, the eleventh a Hiacinth, the twelfth an Amethiſt. And
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:2562:52"/> the twelve gates, were twelve pearles, every ſeverall gate one pearle. And the ſtreete of the City was pure gould as it were tranſparent glaſſe.</hi> Thus farre the Prophet, giving almoſt in every word a touche and deſcription of ſome one or other <hi>Clarity</hi> and brightnes of that <hi>Triumphant City.</hi> O let us ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and ballancing theſe things in the ſcales of our Soules, ſay unto them; <hi>Ariſe ye up and be illightened, for the Light of the Lord is comming, and the glory of God ſhall appeare</hi> both over us and in us if we find truely to feare him ſincerely, to love him, and faithfully to expect his comming, Amen.</p>
                  <p>I have here ſet downe more at large the words of the <hi>Prophet,</hi> that the Godly reader may well obſerve theſe things, firſt what I have ſayd to be moſt true, touching the glorious tranſlucency and ſplendour of the glorified bodyes deſcribed to be like <hi>Iaſper</hi> or <hi>Cryſtal,</hi> or <hi>Saphire</hi> or <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> or ſome other precious pearles, or <hi>Margarites:</hi> the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and ſurpaſſing brightneſſe whereof, eſpecially of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (conformable whereunto the glorified<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 20.</note> bodyes of the Saints <hi>ſhall be made</hi>) I gather out of the 23. verſe of this ſaid chapter, wherein the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet having deſcribed that the glorious City <hi>needeth neither light of the Sunne nor of the Moone, and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reve. 21. 23.</note> 
                     <hi>gives</hi> a reaſon thereof, <hi>for that the Clarity and bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God ſhall illighten the ſame;</hi> he adds in the ſame verſe <hi>that the Candell thereof was the Lambe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Glorious brightneſſe of Chriſts body diſtuſing it ſelfe</note> Who hath ever obſerved a candel, lighted at noon dayes, and bright to have given any light? No, no; the brightneſſe of the Sunne obſcures the ſame, be the candell never ſo great; And yet the <hi>Lambs</hi>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:2562:53"/> clarity and brightneſſe, that is, the brightneſſe of <hi>Chriſt</hi> as man, ſhall through and by his glorified body be ſo ſhining &amp; reſplendant, that it ſhall be as a bright ſhining <hi>Sunne</hi> in that <hi>Triumphant</hi> City, <hi>where ſhall be no night nor darkeneſſe,</hi> ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</p>
                  <p>Againe, I have beene more large in this to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that truth, which ſome moſt idly (as not loving nor deſirous to excell in thoſe vertues which muſt be as meaſures of diſtinct degrees of<note place="margin">Reve. 21. 17.</note> glory; for <hi>one and the ſame is the meaſure of men and Angells</hi>) I ſay as ſome moſt idly would call in queſtion; to weet, that there ſhall be a true <hi>varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and diverſitie of <hi>glories</hi> and glorious <hi>Manſions</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> in that triumphant City; Some cleare like <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall;</hi> ſome bright like <hi>Saphire,</hi> ſome glittering like <hi>Iaſper,</hi> others freſh and greene like <hi>Emerald</hi> &amp;c. Mens Soules ſhall there differ in <hi>glory,</hi> and their bodyes in <hi>Clarity,</hi> even as the ſtarres in the firmament do differ in Clarity each from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This though it be a moſt evident truth, yet the wanton wills of many who have placed al ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity in conceit, apprehenſion, perſwaſion, (I might ſay preſumption) will not admit of the ſame, charme the Charmer never ſo wiſely. But let the pious read ſeriouſly the 20. of this prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,<note place="margin">Reve. 20. 12.</note> and he ſhall finde that the very Iudgements of God touching great and ſmall, (<hi>great and ſmal</hi>) ſhal be according <hi>to what is written in the bookes.</hi> And that the levell meaſure and ſquare is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> according to their workes, that is, <hi>faith, love, patience, zeale, truth,</hi> &amp;c. So juſt is God that he is to all thoſe
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2562:53"/> 
                     <hi>that ſeeke after him</hi> in a holy feare, <hi>a faithfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewarder,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>giving to every man according as he may have done.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe thirdly, I have beene herein the more large, to ſhew the ſurpaſſing felicity of that place; where the whole bodyes of the Saints and every part of them, yea thoſe parts that are now eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med baſeſt and vileſt, ſhall ſhine and glitter like moſt precious <hi>Margarites</hi> and <hi>Pearles:</hi> they ſhall not onely then appeare without blemiſh and free from all deformity; cleare from corruption, without all difficulty; but they ſhall be filled within and compaſſed about without <hi>with Clarity,</hi> they ſhall be indowed and inveſted all over with <hi>Spiritualty;</hi> they ſhall be quickned and enlived with <hi>Agility;</hi> they ſhall be repleniſhed and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 43. 44.</note> with <hi>Impasſibility;</hi> for that which was ſowne in corruption ſhal riſe in incorruption; that which was <hi>ſowne</hi> in <hi>diſhonour</hi> ſhall be raiſed in <hi>glory;</hi> that which was ſowne in <hi>weakeneſſe,</hi> riſing againe in <hi>power;</hi> that which was ſowne a <hi>naturall body,</hi> ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing againe a <hi>ſpirituall body. Seneca</hi> perhaps had ſome obſcure knowledge hereof, when as he writes thus of the ſtate of the Godly after this life ended. <hi>Theſe things</hi> (ſaith he, ſpeaking of the joyes of this life) <hi>ceaſe,</hi> but they periſh <hi>not:</hi> yea,<note place="margin">Seneca. epiſt. 36.</note> 
                     <hi>death which we feare and ſhunne, changeth, but taketh not away life, the day will come</hi> which will place <hi>us in reſt and light:</hi> Thus he, like a Chriſtian, though not ſo fully nor ſo clearely, as that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Father <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Austen</hi> moſt ſweetly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely. <hi>There ſhall be life without death; Youth</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Anguſt. in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loqui.</note>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:2562:54"/> 
                     <hi>without ould age, beawty without deformity; ſtrength without debility,</hi> joy <hi>without</hi> dolour, <hi>reſt without labour, ſuch an aeternall refection ſhall be to the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied bodyes:</hi> thus he. Surely the ſplendour and glory of the body is ſo great, that paſſes all explication, it goes beyond all apprehenſion; and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not onely in reſpect of the happineſſe of the ſoule, but alſo in reſpect of the glory of the body we may well take up that of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 17.</note> 4. 17. <hi>That the momentany and ſhort tribulations of this life doe worke</hi> (in us and for us) <hi>a weight of aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O that the wantons of theſe dayes (ſo full of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and preſumption) who thinke themſelves nobly adorned by their <hi>Pearles, Diamonds</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther coſtly <hi>ornaments,</hi> would ſeriouſly thinke of the glorious and reſplenda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Clarity</hi> of the bodyes of Saints glorified! how would they deſpiſe all thoſe vanities in compariſon, where on now they ſet their fancyes? If we call to minde how <hi>St. Peters</hi> ſoule was <hi>gladded</hi> and raviſhed with the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beholding of <hi>Chriſts</hi> glorified body upon<note place="margin">Mat. 17. 2. Mark. 9. 3.</note> mount <hi>Thabor,</hi> though his body at that time received no part thereof; we cannot otherwiſe thinke, but that the joy of the <hi>beatified</hi> ſhall be exceedingly and ſurpaſſingly great, when they ſhall not onely behold the glorified body of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and ſee his <hi>glory,</hi> but withall ſhall ſee their owne bodyes and ſoules participants of the ſame<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>brightneſſe</hi> and <hi>glory.</hi> So, So, ſhall <hi>God heale the infirmities of his Saints, crowning them in mercyes</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 103. 3. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>and miſerations.</hi> So ſo, ſhall the faithfull <hi>be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:2562:54"/> the ſervitude of Corruption, into the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>of ſuch glory</hi> as beſeemes the Sonnes of God: So, ſo, <hi>ſhall all thoſe who inſtruct others to Godly</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dan. 12. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>life, ſhine as ſtarres in the firmament for all aeternities.</hi> O that our ſoules might be truely enamoured with the love and deſire of this Celeſtiall place and ſtate! O how would we deſpiſe all tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry flaſhes and ſparkes of earthly pleaſures; if we could but ſeriouſly thinke of thoſe joyes and<note place="margin">Pſal. 16. 10.</note> pleaſures, which are layed up in Gods right hand for his Saints for evermore.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſerved ſeven yeares twice told, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine his beautifull <hi>Rachell,</hi> and the dayes though ſo many, ſeemed to him but as few, in reſpect of the greatneſſe of his love. O that the love of our ſoules were in like ſort great after the Celeſtiall <hi>Rachell,</hi> ſo comely in ſtate and glory; then ſhould we think all the labours but light, all the tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance but ſhort, all the dayes but as moments, wherein and wherewith our heauenly <hi>Laban</hi> ſhall exerciſe us in theſe dayes of our <hi>Pilgrimage</hi> and <hi>mortality!</hi> O thou gracious God, Father of <hi>lights,</hi> Illuſtrate our <hi>understandings:</hi> O thou God foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of <hi>life, refreſh</hi> our memories: O thou God, burning fire of love, <hi>enflame</hi> our wills and ſanctifie our affections. O thou God our cheefeſt laſt and only good, the God of our hearts and our portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for ever, be thou to us all in all things. O thou that haſt made us for thy ſelfe, thou haſt framed us ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording <hi>to thy owne Image,</hi> we know none, we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge<note place="margin">Gen. 1. 27.</note> none, nor deſire any other end of our ſelves to make us happy <hi>but thy ſelfe.</hi> O do vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2562:55"/> conduct us ſafe and to bring us ſure to the heaven of thy happineſſe, to the haven of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall felicity: teach us thy paths wherein we ſhall walke, <hi>guide us with thy Counſell, and receive us into thy glory.</hi> To thee we confeſſe in all hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble longing deſires of our ſoules: <hi>Truely O Lord</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Auguſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>q. about the end.</note> 
                     <hi>thou art great aboue all Gods, and great is thy reward,</hi> for thou art not great, and thy reward litle, but as thou art great ſo alſo is thy <hi>reward</hi> great; for thou art not one thing and thy reward another, but <hi>thou thy ſelfe art</hi> the too to great reward; thou the Crowner and the Crowne; <hi>thou the promiſer and the promiſed;</hi> thou <hi>the giver and the gift; thou the rewarder and the reward itſelfe of aeternall felicity. O be thou this to us in the truth of that glory</hi> when we ſhall enter into thy owne joy and ſee thee <hi>as thou art in thy ſelfe: to this guide us with thy Counſell and</hi> enable us with thy Spirit of <hi>grace, that running the way of thy Commandements we may in the end at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thee the God of our hearts, our parts, and our Portion, for ever,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SEVENTH SECTION.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein is breefely and in generall laid downe the meanes and way, whereby eternall happineſſe is to be attained.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>FOr the more cleare handling of this point, we are to ſuppoſe, that whatſoever thing hath any perfection due unto it, as the end and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate perfection thereof; If that perfection
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2562:55"/> be not naturall and eſſentiall to the thing it ſelfe; the ſame cannot be had without ſome <hi>action</hi> or <hi>motion</hi> leading thereunto: for example, <hi>God</hi> who<note place="margin">Exod. 3. 14.</note> is moſt eſſentially his owne (<hi>I am that I am</hi>) and whole infinite perfection is his owne being, moſt neceſſarily and eſſentially; needes not nor requires not, any action or motion to any thing that is without himſelfe for his end and perfection. But ſo it is not in Creatures, whoſe natures being li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and in themſelves imperfect, neede and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſome action or motion to that which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out themſelves, for the attaining of their ends and final perfection; which motion is that which now we have in handling, whereby man is to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his laſt end, and conſummate happines.</p>
               <p>For this purpoſe I ponder that Principle of the Apoſtle, <hi>He that cometh to God muſt beleeve that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11 6.</note> 
                  <hi>he is, and that he is a rewarder of all thoſe that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after him.</hi> In which words I find clearely, that the <hi>acceſſion</hi> and comming to <hi>God</hi> in this life, (which is the way to that <hi>viſion</hi> and <hi>fruition</hi> of God in the nextlife, the finall end of man) is by <hi>Faith,</hi> and a religious <hi>inquiſition</hi> of and after him, which religious <hi>inquiſition</hi> of and after him, if I ſhould thinke not to be cheifely by <hi>Faith, hope</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> (as the heads of this way out of which many particular paths doe follow) I ſhould wrong the judgement of all <hi>Orthodoxe</hi> Divines whatſoever; who doe diſtinguiſh the vertues that are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and immediately exerciſed upon and about God into three, to weet, <hi>Faith Hope</hi> and <hi>Love.</hi> The later of which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> himſelfe termes
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2562:56"/> the <hi>more excellent way;</hi> writing thus to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cor. 12. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>And yet ſhew I you a more excellent way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> which more excellent way alone, is to be taken as the <hi>ſpirit</hi> and <hi>path</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> againe, is to be reputed as the <hi>head</hi> way and <hi>ſoule</hi> of it, two in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuall &amp; inſeparable <hi>twinnes,</hi> mutually ever <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing</hi> each other and <hi>working</hi> each by other.</p>
               <p>And though there bee infinite ianglings and queſtions, about the vertue, extent and cauſalitie of theſe ſeverall vertues in the matter of juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and about their manner of <hi>merrit</hi> or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence</hi> to <hi>ſaluation,</hi> yet doe I not remember, that ever I have read of any, except the ungodly <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomiſts</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt: ad quod vult de<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hereſ. 14.</note> and prophane <hi>Libertines</hi> (a broode of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomius</hi>) or ſome indiſcret <hi>Predicants,</hi> who have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the neceſſitie of the two later; <hi>hope</hi> and <hi>love;</hi> As for the firſt, Faith, all requyre the ſame abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to ſalvation; Yea the Papiſts themſelves require the ſame as the very <hi>firſt</hi> meanes <hi>and foundation for juſtification</hi> and <hi>ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coun: Trident Bellar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Omnes Pontificii.</note> out of an abſolute neceſſitie: but not ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and alone without <hi>hope</hi> and <hi>loue.</hi> The Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Churches</hi> generally, hould her, (to weet <hi>faith</hi>) to be the ſole and onely inſtrumentall cauſe of <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> by which as by a <hi>hand,</hi> the juſtice &amp; righteouſneſſe of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is applyed unto the <hi>juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> ſoule. So then by confeſſion of all, an <hi>acceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and motion to God there muſt be in this life, or elſe there can be no poſſeſſion of him in <hi>frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in the next life. The <hi>happineſſe</hi> of this life, is the way and motion to the <hi>happineſſe</hi> of the next life. The happineſſe of the next life (which is the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:2562:56"/> happineſſe of the end) can be no other then the <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> and <hi>fruition</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> The happineſſe of this life which is the happineſſe of the way, is alſo a <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> and <hi>fruition</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> but it is by faith and love; and that which <hi>Euſebius</hi> calleth, <hi>the worſhip of God,</hi> not onely <hi>externall,</hi> but eſpecially <hi>internall,</hi> and yet not ſo internall, but that there muſt alſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily<note place="margin">Euſib. de mouſt evanglica.</note> be externall, <hi>for no man ſhal be crowned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he ſhall manfully and lawfully have fought:</hi> and<note place="margin">2 Timoth. 2. 5.</note> againe, the Spirit of God ſaith thus, <hi>Hould that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reve. 3. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>which thou haſt, leſt another take thy crowne.</hi> Which wee are not onely to underſtand of the internall ſight of the ſoule, and inward conſtancy of our <hi>Faith,</hi> but alſo of the outward profeſſion thereof,<note place="margin">Rom. 10. 10.</note> and the externall exerciſe of <hi>piety</hi> and <hi>godlineſſe;</hi> If I be demaunded what I would call this, I cannot bethinke of a better name then <hi>Chriſtian warfare,</hi> or the <hi>Imitation of Chriſt.</hi> The holy <hi>Apoſtle</hi> chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring<note place="margin">Tit. 2. 12.</note> up the faithfull, puts them in minde of a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>expectation</hi> after the <hi>comming of the glory of the great God;</hi> but he prefixes before by the way of neceſſary <hi>preparation;</hi> that they muſt live <hi>ſoberly, piouſly,</hi> and <hi>justly in this world:</hi> ſo that <hi>ſobriety</hi> (which conteines the well ordering of man in himſelfe,) againſt exceſſe &amp;c. <hi>Piety,</hi> which comprehends the whole worſhip of <hi>God, Iustice</hi> which compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes all duties that appertaine to <hi>equity,</hi> &amp; right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt man and man; are prerequired as the very <hi>motion</hi> and <hi>way,</hi> by which they ſhall come to the ioyous <hi>meeting</hi> and glorious enioying of the <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Via Regni.</note> 
                  <hi>of the great God.</hi> Thus then <hi>holy life and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an workes, are the very way and motion, to the glorious
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:2562:57"/> viſion and fraition of God.</hi> It is ſaid generally, yea received by all <hi>Orthodoxe</hi> Divines, that good and godly workes are the way to <hi>the kingdome of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi> Which we are not to underſtand by the way of compariſon onely to the materiall way, by which men in their corporall journies, doe walke from place to place, from Citie to citie; but even by the way of compariſon, to the <hi>very motions, walkings and paſſings of men upon and along the ſame wayes;</hi> which we may call mens wayes to ſuch and ſuch places: ſo the pious and godly life of the faithfull, <hi>is</hi> their very <hi>moving, paſſing</hi> and <hi>walking</hi> to their journies end, the glorious <hi>viſion</hi> and <hi>frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of God. And ſo in what manner wee may hold the <hi>movings</hi> and <hi>paſſings</hi> of men along their wayes, neceſſary for their arriving to ſuch and ſuch places: In like ſort we muſt hould the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and paſſing of man by godly life, to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for his arriving to the <hi>kingdome</hi> of <hi>glory. No man,</hi> ſaith that Reverend Paſtour <hi>Cowper, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cowper apud D. Boyes, 8. Sonday after Trinit. epiſt.</note> 
                  <hi>either to priſon or pallace, but by the entrie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi> So man goeth to <hi>heaven</hi> or <hi>hell,</hi> but <hi>by the way thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If this which I have ſet downe, touching good workes, the very way of man to his eternall feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, were not apparent in it ſelfe according to the tenure of ſacred ſcriptures, requiring &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the ſame; yet the very manner of <hi>Chriſts</hi> inveſting and inducting his <hi>Saints</hi> with, and into glory, doth moſt evidently evince the ſame. For<note place="margin">Mat. 25. 22. 23. 24.</note> were it not a diſhonour againſt the infinite pure <hi>Majestie</hi> of God, and impeachment to his all<note place="margin">Luk. 19. 17.</note>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:2562:57"/> 
                  <hi>knowledge,</hi> and wiſdome, to thinke that he ſhould otherwiſe give glory in time, then in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as he from all <hi>aeternities</hi> foreknew hee would give, and had predetermined to give? Or that he ſhould not from al <hi>aeternities</hi> have foredetermined, &amp; decreed ſo to give <hi>glory;</hi> as in the time of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of his <hi>Saints</hi> into <hi>glorie,</hi> he doth actually give &amp; in truth of thing <hi>collate</hi> the ſame. Now how God doth actually giue &amp; collate <hi>glory</hi> at the day of <hi>glorification,</hi> the Goſpell is ſo cleere, that there is no declaration or amplificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, for he admitteth into his kingdome of <hi>glorie,</hi> thoſe that have beleeved in him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved him; even as from all <hi>eternities</hi> he had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared<note place="margin">Iſa. 64. 4. 1 Cor. 2. 9.</note> the glorie, <hi>which eye hath not ſeene, nor eare heard, nor heart conceived, for thoſe that love him.</hi> Love him, is expreſſed, but beleeve on him, is ſuppoſed: For it is not leſſe poſſible to love <hi>God</hi> without <hi>Faith,</hi> then it is poſſible to pleaſe him without <hi>faith,</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> concludeth to be altogether impoſſible. And thus doe the good<note place="margin">Heb. 11. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>workes of the faithfull follow them.</hi> So, ſo, the <hi>Virgins,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reve. 14. 13.</note> that <hi>have light and Oyle in their Lampes,</hi> with joy<note place="margin">Mat. 25. 10.</note> finde admittance into the <hi>joye</hi> of the <hi>Bridgroome.</hi> So, ſo, all thoſe that have on their <hi>weding garments</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 11. 12.</note> are graciouſly admitted, all others wanting the ſame, are juſtly excluded. So, ſo, the iuſt judge that gives <hi>to every man according to his workes,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeth his diligent and faithfull <hi>Servants,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee findeth <hi>watchfull;</hi> and by their piety and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,<note place="margin">Mat. 25. 20. 22.</note> in the <hi>good</hi> uſe of <hi>grace,</hi> (and this by grace) to have gained either <hi>five, two</hi> or more <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents,</hi> according to the meaſure of grace recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:2562:58"/> So ſo are good works <hi>via regni, the way to the kingdome!</hi> as it is the joynt voice of all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>God.</hi> But yet we muſt know this very well, that we muſt not attribute eternall life, nor the means that leade thereunto, to any other, then to the <hi>grace of God.</hi> Concerning which truth, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable <hi>Auſten</hi> after a long diſcourſe concludeth<note place="margin">Auguſt. de grat. et lib. arbit. c. 8. et 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15. 16. &amp;c.</note> thus, <hi>Therefore moſt deare,</hi> our <hi>good and godly life is nothing elſe,</hi> but <hi>the grace of God,</hi> and without doubt <hi>life everlasting, which is given to good life, is the grace of God;</hi> for it alſo <hi>is given, becauſe that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which it is given, is freely given;</hi> but that to which it is <hi>given is onely grace; but this which is given to it, becauſe it is a reward thereof, it is a grace for a grace, as it were a reward for Righteouſneſſe, that that may be true, (becauſe it is true) that God will reward every</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>man according to his works,</hi> thus he: Which being ſo, as it is moſt evide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſo, that the life of Glory, is given <hi>too</hi> and according to the life of grace and ſanctitie: O let vs all with joye and alacrity, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound more and more therein, adding <hi>vertue &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 5. 6.</note> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> adviſeth; that this life being ended, and our <hi>races</hi> couragiouſly run through, wee may gloriouſly bee exalted into the vpper houſe of <hi>Gods</hi> glory, and <hi>Eternitie.</hi> O gracious God, how happie is hee whom thou ſhalt <hi>vouchſafe ſo to teach</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 94. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>and instruct in thy Law,</hi> that dutiefully <hi>walking therein,</hi> hee may in the end, come to behold thee the <hi>God of Gods, in thy Caeleſtiall Sion.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 84. 8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo here, as I cannot but obſerve, ſo I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but lament the infinite janglings of diverſe, touching the cauſality of good works, to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:2562:58"/> whether it be of <hi>condignity</hi> or <hi>congruity,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be as <hi>conditions (without which, not)</hi> as <hi>merrits.</hi> For cleere it is, that they are ſo neceſſary to <hi>Salvation,</hi> as the way thereunto, ſo that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, <hi>ſalvation ſhall never be had.</hi> In <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy</hi> it is moſt true, <hi>from one extreame to another, no man can paſſe, but by &amp; over the middle.</hi> So likewiſe in <hi>Divinity</hi> it is moſt true, that no man can paſſe from the <hi>extreame</hi> of ſinfull miſery, but by the <hi>middell</hi> and <hi>meanes</hi> of godly <hi>life</hi> and <hi>piety.</hi> When the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſhewes, what manner of <hi>Cauſalitie</hi> the paſſing along vpon the way, hath for the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers comming to the wayes end, then may the <hi>Divine</hi> in like ſort, declare what manner of <hi>cauſalitie,</hi> the walking and going on along in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, may have for the attaining unto the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>life everlaſting:</hi> what neede ſuch diſputes? O how better is it to have an inward, true ſenſe and teſtimony of <hi>juſtification,</hi> then to have ſuch wrang ling and fooliſh <hi>logomachie</hi> about the formalitie of <hi>Iustification?</hi> We all on all ſides, (I except the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witted <hi>Preciſians</hi> and <hi>Libertines, Browniſts</hi> and <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts</hi>) require faith <hi>as neceſſary,</hi> yea, <hi>as abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation.</hi> What neede then ſuch hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſputes about the <hi>cauſality</hi> of them, to <hi>ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi> Let all rather endevour to abound in them, then to diſpute of them, <hi>for ſo an abundant meanes of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>into glorie, and of attaining their laſt endes ſhall be miniſtred unto them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How idle might that <hi>Duke</hi> or <hi>Prince,</hi> be thought to be, who being called by any free and powerfull <hi>State</hi> to be their <hi>abſolute Lord</hi> and <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne,</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:2562:59"/> ſhould firſt before he would goe to take the ſaid <hi>Crowne</hi> diſpute with his <hi>Sages,</hi> what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>cauſality,</hi> his going in Coatch or riding on horſebacke, might have for the attainement of the <hi>ſame?</hi> Is it not enough for the <hi>Duke</hi> to know that he cannot be <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>King</hi> except he make his <hi>profection</hi> and his going to the <hi>place</hi> where this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour muſt be beſtowed on him? Againe, is it not enough for him that is in danger of ſhipwracke, to know that he ſhall periſh together with the ſhip, unleſſe by ſome convenient meanes he eſcape to the land? How unwiſe ſhould thoſe have beene reputed who being in <hi>St. Paules</hi> company and in<note place="margin">Act. 27. 44.</note> danger of ſhipwrack, ſhould have refuſed to have taken either board or planke whercon to ſwimme to the ſhore, before the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> had declared in expreſſe tearmes what manner of <hi>cauſaltty</hi> the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of ſuch boardes and the ſwimming out upon them ſhould have had for their deliverance? Is it not ſufficient for the gameſter and wraſtler to know that except he contend manfully and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily he ſhall have no reward? So, ſo; let it be aboundantly ſufficient for <hi>Christians</hi> to <hi>know</hi> and underſtand, that unleſſe they <hi>fight a good fight, they</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Timoth. 2. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall not be crowned; unleſſe they hould faſt that which</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reve. 3. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>they have, another ſhall take their crowne: unleſſe their righteouſneſſe abound more then the righteouſneſſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Scribes and Phariſes, they ſhall not enter into the Kingdome of Heaven. Vnleſſe they be diligent and painefull labourers in the vineyard, they ſhall receive no</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 20. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>day penney: unleſſe they have the cable of faith and repentance, they ſhall not avoyd ſhipwracke:</hi> except
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:2562:59"/> they <hi>perſevere in faith and piety unto the end,</hi> they <hi>ſhall never attaine that laſt happy end, ſalvation.</hi> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, that according to their very workes, ſo they ſhall receive; either <hi>glory honour and immortalite;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5 10. Reve. 10. 12. Rom. 2. 9 10.</note> 
                  <hi>or ſhame, diſhonour, anguiſh and confuſion,</hi> as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle St. Paule</hi> hath plainely delivered, and <hi>St. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> moſt reſolutely: <hi>Of a truth I have found that there is no acception of perſons with God, but in every nation hee that feareth him, and worketh righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 10. 34. 35</note> 
                  <hi>is accepted with him.</hi> Thus the word of God moſt clearely: <hi>accurſed</hi> then be he that <hi>addeth or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracteth any thing, or diſputes againſt this truth;</hi> ſo clearely delivered, ſo ſtrongly confirmed.</p>
               <p>Venerable <hi>Auſten</hi> reproved ſome raſh and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous<note place="margin">Auguſt. de vit. Chriſt. cap. 14. 10. 6.</note> wits of his times, daring to blaſpheme againſt this truth. <hi>And I have knowne others</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>whom the darke and obſcure cloud of folly and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence ſo deludeth</hi> and deceiveth, that they <hi>thinke and affirme, that the faith which they pretend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to have ſhall profit them without workes of juſtice before God; &amp; being deceived with this kynd of errour, without al feare they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit greivous crimes, whilst they beleeve God to be onely a revenger and Puniſher of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 15. 14. Luc. 6. 39.</note> 
                  <hi>but not of other crimes. And ſuch as theſe are not content themſelves to periſh alone, but they alſo endevour to entrappe others, in whom there is no light of divine knowledge, and the ſentence of our Saviour is fulfilled in them. The blinde if he lead the blinde they ſhall both fall into the ditch.</hi> Thus he: which cenſure of his doth it not concerne thoſe who in theſe dayes dare affirme that <hi>Obedience</hi> appertaines not to the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and that of the <hi>lawe, do this
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:2562:60"/> and thou ſhalt live,</hi> appertaines not to <hi>the Goſpell;</hi> and againe, that whatſoever ſinnes the elect may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, <hi>they are not leſſe acceptable in the</hi> ſight of God. By which prodigious <hi>paradoxes</hi> it is evident, that they have placed all religion in <hi>apprehenſion</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, which in the end will but deceave them.</p>
               <p>Thus having in generall ſhewed the way to the laſt end of man (endleſſe happineſſe and felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) to be <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>pious godly life,</hi> it ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe to adde a few words, touching that <hi>ſource</hi> &amp; <hi>roote,</hi> whereout and whence out, a <hi>godly and pious life</hi> doth ſpring, yea ſolely and infallibly doth ſpring and ariſe.</p>
               <p>Cleare it is, that the <hi>life</hi> of every man is called his daily <hi>ſtudy,</hi> and <hi>converſation;</hi> and as cleere it is, that the daily ſtudie and converſation of every man, are the vſuall <hi>actions</hi> and <hi>operations</hi> of every man; which <hi>actions</hi> and <hi>operations</hi> if pious &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, leading to glorie, they muſt needes proceede from a man <hi>renewed</hi> in <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and <hi>regenerate</hi> in his <hi>ſoule:</hi> ſo that though the very faculties &amp; powers of the ſoule, to weet, the <hi>underſtanding, will,</hi> and <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie</hi> with ſuch like, doe really and truely effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and produce ſuch actions and operations, yet they doe it by the <hi>vertue</hi> and efficacy of <hi>grace</hi> which is in them; <hi>I</hi> (ſayeth the <hi>Apoſtle) have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>more then they all, but not I, but the grace-of God which is with me;</hi> or thus, <hi>which is in me,</hi> or thus, <hi>with me;</hi> upholding divers readings. Againe <hi>Chriſt to</hi> his faithfull, <hi>when you ſhall ſtand before your adverſaries,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 21. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>do yee not premeditate what or how to ſpeake, for I will give unto you a mouth and wiſdome, which all your
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:2562:60"/> adverſaries ſhall not be able to withſtand; for it is not you that ſpeake, but the Spirit of my Father which is in you.</hi> Of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> it is affirmed, <hi>that they were</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 2. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>all filled with the holy Ghoſt, and beganne to ſpeake as the holy Ghoſt gave them utter ante.</hi> So in theſe, ſo in all actions godly, and ſupernaturall, man worketh according to that meaſure of grace which is given unto him: When given unto him? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Ephe, 4 7.</note> moſt ſpecially in <hi>Regeneration, where as that which</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>is borne of the ſpirit is become Spirit, not by ceaſing</hi> to be that ſubſtantiall naturall ſpirit which it was<note place="margin">Iſa. 11. 2. Galat. 5. 22. Epheſ. 4. 23. 24. Rom. 8. 20. 21.</note> before, but becauſe <hi>invested</hi> in herſelfe, and in every faculty of herſelfe, with the gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Spirit; ſhe is by them truely <hi>renewed</hi> and <hi>innovated,</hi> yea changed from the ſervitude of ſin full corruption, <hi>into the libertie of the children of God.</hi> Yea, ſo changed, that by the Spirit of God<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 17. Galat. 6. 15. Epheſ. 5. 6. 2 Cor. 6. 7.</note> they are called <hi>new Creatures, light in the Lord, Temples of God, ſeates of wiſdome,</hi> with many ſuch like glorious appellations: And no marvell, for the <hi>graces</hi> and <hi>gifts</hi> of the Spirit of God are ſo deare, and ſo gracious, that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> dares to affirme, that by them the faithfull <hi>are made</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Partakers of the Divine nature it ſelfe.</hi> And theſe graces and giftes precious, ſo called by Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> are the very <hi>Source, roote,</hi> or fountaine of all thoſe graces and motions which leade to <hi>aternity:</hi> and theſe graces the <hi>Apostle</hi> intendeth, when he thus divinely admoniſheth, <hi>It is good to confirme and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh the heart with grace, &amp; not with meates, which</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>have not profited thoſe which walked in them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the reaſon why the ſweete providence of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:2562:61"/> God doth inveſt the <hi>Regenerate</hi> ſoules with theſe <hi>graces</hi> and <hi>precious giftes,</hi> whereby the <hi>holy Ghost is ſaid to dwell</hi> in them; is not onely, becauſe they ſhould have internall <hi>garments</hi> of <hi>ſanctitie,</hi> befit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his ſervice, but alſo becauſe, he would have thoſe that doe his ſervice and be his ſervants, to doe him <hi>acceptable ſervice,</hi> yea, ſuch acceptable <hi>ſervice,</hi> as may leade and conduct them to <hi>glory immortall.</hi> He made man without man, (man in his making doing nothing), but he wil not ſo ſave man doing nothing, hand in hand, leaning his <hi>ſoules elbowes,</hi> on the cuſhion of <hi>preſumption: no no, hee will not ſave man,</hi> without man (as <hi>Austen</hi> truely) not becauſe man with &amp; by virtue of his naturall power can cooperate with God, to <hi>ſalvation;</hi> but becauſe man being in his ſoule and powers thereof, <hi>changed, renewed,</hi> and enabled, by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious giftes of grace; <hi>ſhall and</hi> may <hi>cooperate to his ſalvation:</hi> yea the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> dares to profeſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 9.</note> and ſuch like to be <hi>Gods-helpers,</hi> in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of ſalvation.</p>
               <p>If <hi>God</hi> did not requyre mans good and pious converſation, as a meanes and neceſſary way lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>ſalvation,</hi> then ſhould not the faculties &amp; powers of mans <hi>ſoule</hi> neede to be <hi>ſanctified,</hi> and <hi>elevated</hi> with ſuch ſupernaturall <hi>giftes and graces,</hi> for the working and effecting of ſuch actions, of <hi>pietie</hi> and <hi>godlines:</hi> but ſeeing he requires them, yea moſt neceſſarily requires them, as welnye every page of ſacred <hi>Scripture</hi> proclaimes; it ſhould ſeeme a kinde of iniquity in <hi>God</hi> (which be farre from him) to require ſuch actions of man, yea
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:2562:61"/> and to condemne for the want of them, if hee ſhould not by his graces be ready to enable man for the doing and performing of the ſame. Hee doth it then, and this ſurely, by no other meanes then by inveſting the ſoule and every power of her, with ſuch divine <hi>gifts, graces</hi> and <hi>vertues,</hi> as ſo divine actions doe require. <hi>Bernard</hi> truely to<note place="margin">Bern. ſer. 83. in canſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> this purpoſe, <hi>The ſoule cannot ſeeke after God, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſhe be prevented by grace. Auſten</hi> more fully, <hi>Grace</hi> is <hi>therefore given, not becauſe wee have done works, but that we may doe them;</hi> that is, not <hi>becauſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. 105. a ſixt: to 2 circa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med.</note> 
                  <hi>we have kept the law, but that wee may keepe the law.</hi> And againe, <hi>Even as</hi> man <hi>ſhould not have wiſedome, underſtanding, counſell, fortitude, knowledge, piety, the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 11. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>feare of God, except according to the</hi> Propheticall ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he had received the Spirit <hi>of wiſedome and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and counſell and fortitude, and knowledge and piety, and the feare of God: and even as he ſhould not have vertue, charity, continency, except he ſhould have received the holy Spirit, whereof the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, you have not received the Spirit of feare, but of vertue, charitie, contineney; ſo neither ſhould hee have faith, unleſſe he had received the Spirit of faith, according as it is written, I have beleeved &amp; therefore</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 115.</note> 
                  <hi>I have ſpoken, and we alſo doe beleeve, and therefore wee ſpeake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then, the <hi>ſource,</hi> roote and <hi>fountaine,</hi> of all theſe godly <hi>actions,</hi> and motions, which leade to <hi>ſalvation,</hi> are the <hi>graces</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> becauſe procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from his <hi>graces</hi> enabling us for them; which<note place="margin">Sap. 10. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>graces he, who hateth nothing of all that he hath made,</hi> he that <hi>willeth all ſhould be ſaved, and come to the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:2562:62"/> knowledge of his truth:</hi> He, <hi>who delighteth not in the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Timoth. 2. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>death of a ſinner, but that he turne from his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezec<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 33. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>and live.</hi> He <hi>who lightneth every man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 1. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>into the world.</hi> Hee <hi>who hath placed his Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle in the Sunne to runne his race with ſwiftnes, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 19. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>to ſpread his beames with graciouſneſſe, that nothing can ſcape the warmth of his illuminations.</hi> He <hi>who</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reve. 3. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtandeth at the dore and knocketh, that if any man o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to him, he will enter in, ſup with him, and bee his gueſt.</hi> He I ſay, who is out of his goodneſſe thus<note place="margin">Reve. 22. 17.</note> graciouſly diſpoſed towards his creatures, <hi>freely</hi> and frankely offers and preſents the ſame unto them: in a holy ſerious manner, that they may have life, <hi>yea, have it more abundantly,</hi> according<note place="margin">Ioh. 10. 10.</note> to that of himſelfe, <hi>I am come that they may have life, and have it more aboundantly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus it appeareth how by grace preſented and received (received by the efficacy of it ſelfe) the <hi>Saints</hi> and ſervants of God do walke in thoſe wayes where by they come to be ſaved; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are enabled in ſome good meaſure truely to doe that which otherwiſe ſhould be impoſſible to nature vitiated and corrupted. <hi>Auſten</hi> for<note place="margin">De grat. et lib. arbitrio cap. 16 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>07.</note> this purpoſe excellently thus. <hi>It is certaine</hi> we may keepe the Commandements, if wee <hi>will; but becauſe the will muſt be prepared by the Lord, we muſt aske of him that we may have a will to do ſo much as wee ought willingly to doe. It is certeine that we do then well when we will, but he maketh us able that we may will good, of whom that is written,</hi> which I <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed a litle aboue; The</hi> will is prepared <hi>of the Lord: of whom it is ſaid; The wayes of men are directed of the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:2562:62"/> Lord. And he it is that willeth their way of whom it is ſaid, It is God that doth worke in us both to will &amp; to doe. It is certaine that we doe when we doe; but he maketh that we may doe, giving most powerfull ſtrength and ability to the will,</hi> who hath ſaid, I <hi>will make you able that you may walke in my juſtifications, and keepe, and doe my judgements.</hi> Thus he, moſt excellently declaring the working of grace in us, and our working by grace. Grace the reward whereof is eternall life, and our good keeping of Gods Commandements in a partiall meaſure according to this ſtate, not in a full &amp; perfect mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of degrees. Thus concluding theſe my meditations touching the laſt end of man, I earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intreate the religious <hi>Reader,</hi> ſeriouſly to thinke and meditate on the <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>aeternity</hi> of this <hi>Land of promiſe</hi> both ſhewed and promiſed ſo faithfully and ſeriouſly unto him in ſacred <hi>Scriptures.</hi> The <hi>glories</hi> and <hi>excellencies</hi> thereof do infinitely ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe the fruites, that were brought unto the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of the <hi>Land</hi> of promiſe, which<note place="margin">Num. 13. 28.</note> notwithſtanding did ſo prevaile on the hearts of the faithfull, that the deſire to obtaine the ſaid fruits enabled them with a ſpirit of courage to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe all perills and hazards for the attaining of them; many there were indeed whom the ſpirit of feare and trembling reſtreined from going into that happy land, becauſe they heard that the ſonnes of <hi>Enacim, giants,</hi> robuſtious men were therein; and thereby periſhed deſervedly for their incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and diſobedience: Oh let not the like ſpirit of <hi>Incredulity</hi> and <hi>diſobedience</hi> have dominion over
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:2562:63"/> the hearts of any <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> I eſpecially meane thoſe who profeſſe to know God arightly; for if we know God arightly, let us walke to him <hi>arightly, diligently, fervently.</hi> O gracious God, thou the onely wiſe and moſt powerfull God, doe thou vouchſafe for thy deare <hi>Sonnes</hi> ſake, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large and widen our ſtreightened hearts by the Spirit of grace: that we may runne to thee, and in the end alſo attaine thee, by the <hi>way of thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements</hi> preſet to us by thy ſelfe. To my ſoule I ſay and reſolue, that it be praying to God the Father in his Sonns name, that ſhee may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed with ſuch a ſpirit of grace, that enamoured with the conſideration and love of this happines, ſhee may in the imitation of that holy man ever breathe out thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O my ſoule, if we ought continually, to endure tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that we may ſee Christ in his glory with God the Father, and to be aſſociated to the fellowſhip of his Saints; were it not meete, patiently, and willingly, to ſuffer all that is ſorrowfull, that we might bee made partakers of ſo great a good; and ſo great a glory?</hi> Let the Devills therefore lye in <hi>waite,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>their temptations, let fastings and hard-clothings breake and ſub due our bodies,</hi> let <hi>labours oppreſſe, wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings afflict, let that man diſquyet me, this man crie out againſt me, let cold bowe and pinch me, heate burne me, let my head ake, my brest faint, my ſtomacke ſwell, my face waxe wanne, &amp; pale, let me in every part be weakened, and let my life faile me in griefe &amp; ſorrow, my ſoule in mourning &amp; heavineſſe; let rottennes enter into my bones and abound under me, ſo that I may find
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:2562:63"/> reſt in the day of Tribulation, and may aſcend up to the people of God. O</hi> my God, giue me a <hi>ſpirit</hi> to awake early in the morning unto thee, and that my <hi>ſoule may thirſt after thee, yea that my very fleſh may be manifeſtly and manyfoldly even bent unto thee.</hi> O be thou the <hi>Horizon of my heart at noone day, the deſire of my ſoule at midnight.</hi> O let all that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me long after thee, that I may in the end <hi>come to ſee and behold thee; as thou art in thy ſelfe, my bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed end, my happineſſe, the God of my heart, my part, and my portion for ever AMEN.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Recenſui hunc Tractatum, cui Titulus eſt [<hi>Mans last end &amp;c.</hi>] (unà cum Epiſtola De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatoria ad Sereniſſimum Regem <hi>Carolum,</hi> et praefatione ad Lectorem.) qui quidem liber continet, pag. 83. in quibus omnibus nihil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perio ſanae doctrinae, aut bonis moribus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarium, quo minus cum utilitate publica im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primatur, ita tamen ut ſi non intra ſeptem men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes proxime ſequentes Typis mandetur, haec licentia ſit omnino irrita.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ex aedibus</hi> Fulhamienſibus <hi>prid.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Calend. Septem.</hi> 1633.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Guil. Bray.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>The Errata</head>
            <p>Page 10. lin 8. for that, read and p. 20. l. 5. reade, is his end. pa. 57 l. 29, for him r, ſinne. p. 82, l. 30. for roule, r. walke. pa. 87, r. If we be found. p, 99, l. 2, r. or as me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rits pag 100. l, 31, r. table of faith. p. 102, l. 29, according to diverſe readings.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notes">
            <head>In the notes.</head>
            <p>Pag 25, read preſences. pa, 43, for Trinitate, r, Civitate. pag 60, r, q. 82. p. 68, r. 19. p. 103. r. Cor. v, 16.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
